<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the knovvledge of God, as excellently as compendiously handled by the famous and learned divine, Peter Du Moulin, late minister of the Reformed Church in Paris, and professor of theologie in the Vniversitie of Sedan. Faithfully translated out of the originall by Robert Codrington, Master of Arts</title>
            <title>De cognitione Dei. English</title>
            <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A20943</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118646</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853853</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853853</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A20943)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1095:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the knovvledge of God, as excellently as compendiously handled by the famous and learned divine, Peter Du Moulin, late minister of the Reformed Church in Paris, and professor of theologie in the Vniversitie of Sedan. Faithfully translated out of the originall by Robert Codrington, Master of Arts</title>
                  <title>De cognitione Dei. English</title>
                  <author>Du Moulin, Pierre, 1568-1658.</author>
                  <author>Codrington, Robert, 1601-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 72, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. M[athewes] and are to be sold by William Sheares, at the signe of the Harrow in Britaines-Bursse, and at his shop neere Yorke-house,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>God --  Proof --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Apologetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE KNOVV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEDGE OF GOD, As excellently as compendiouſly hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the famous and learned Divine, PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER DV MOVLIN, late Miniſter of the Reformed Church in Paris, and Profeſſor of Theologie in the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of Sedan. Faithfully tranſlated out of the Originall By ROBERT CODRINGTON, Maſter of Arts.</p>
            <q>This is life eternall to know thee to be the onely very God, and whom thou haſt ſent Ieſus Chriſt,</q>
            <bibl>Iohn, 17.</bibl>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by A. M. and are to be ſold by William Sheares, at the ſigne of the Harrow in Britaines-Burſſe, and at his ſhop neere Yorke-houſe. 1634.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, AND vertuous Lady, <hi>Alice,</hi> Counteſſe of <hi>Darby, Strange, Le Knocking,</hi> Vice-Counteſſe of <hi>Kinton, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He report and ſplendour of your Vertues haue encouraged mee to preſent theſe Papers into your honourable hand, in which, what my preſumption hath of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, my duety may excuſe; it being Religion to pay moſt homage unto thoſe ſhrines which moſt Vertues have erected; &amp; Fame ſo loud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly celebrating your praiſes, it were ſome rebellion in mee not to attend, or infidelity not to believe her Story, which pronounceth you the Mirrour and Bleſsing of this Age, to bee as great a wonder as an example to Poſterity, &amp; eminent in all your actions, which as they are advanced by your Greatneſſe, ſo they are crowned by your Goodneſſe; Goodneſſe it ſelfe being ſo habituall unto you, that it ſeemes ſhe is become even your nature, and may be called as much your complexion as your practice.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:3"/>
            <p>This is that which hath invited me to the Dedicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this Treatiſe to your Honour; for to whom more worthily could I preſent it then to you, whoſe life is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentarie on it, making Religion not your affectation, but your moſt ſevere imployment, and the excellence of your ſpirit, although it workes you to a nobler height then our duller faculties can attaine unto, yet the height of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is ſtill the humility of your Vertue, and it is the laſt of your praiſes not to affect them. This I have received from the mouth of Fame, which I deliuer not to your eares, but to the truth of your Story, which parallels your love to Learning with the nobleneſſe of your other Vertues, and preferres your love unto Religion aboue them. Vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe then, <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> to accept this Treatiſe, not unworthy of ſo Noble a Patronage; and if my devotion to your Honour can winne on your Goodneſſe to pardon my Preſumption, the excellence of the Subject ſhall winne on your Iudgement to entertaine the Treatiſe, in which there is no other errour to be found, but that it is preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the World, and You, by this rude hand of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours moſt humbly deuoted R. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_readers">
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Tranſlatour</hi> to the <hi>Readers.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Treatiſe needs not a Preface to entertaine you, or encourage you; the title it ſelf is eloquent enough, yet Cuſtome expecteth that ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be ſpoken of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, &amp; the Author: and it were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannerly beſides, at my firſt comming abroad, to preſſe into your acquaintance without ſaluting you. As there is nothing then more excellent than this Subject; ſo there is no man that could diſcourſe on it more excellently then the Author, the Author abounding with the Subject, and directing the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to that knowledge by which he wrote it. The Atheiſt may here learne as well how to worſhip as to believe a Deity, and reading the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode of his wiſedome in the Characters of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, may as well be convinced by Reaſon as Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. The Epicure may acknowledge the looſe impiety of his Idoll pleaſures, and engaged in more holy and high devotions may performe no more homage to his purſive God. The Recuſant may perceive that Heaven is not to be bribed by his merites or his money, but may here finde his ſalvation more cheape, and certaine. The Treatiſe is but ſmall, but what wants in the volume is ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb facs="tcp:19251:4"/> in the Subject: it was borne in the Engliſh aire, though not in the Engliſh tongue, this is the Fate of Bookes to be eloquent at firſt, and to ſpeake in variety of tongues, the diverſity of languages being by them promoted into a bleſſing, and they ſeeme like ſo many inſpirations, and to be Prophets of that knowledge which our underſtandings all ſhall enjoy hereafter. This then being ſo expert in other languages, it was pitty me thought it ſhould want his own, and had only the power to perſwade me to this work attended with a deſire which I had by the imparting of our Authors knowledge to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your owne, a deſire which (where they are legible in earneſt) can excuſe abſurdities, and even ſanctify the Errours; but I write an Epiſtle, not an Apology, and am neither doubtfull of mine owne integrity, or indulgent to the faults of others, whom I am ſo farre from flattering, that I muſt pronounce to excuſe them is a ſacriledge, and to conceale them the lowdeſt ſlander, theſe are they who with impure hands doe tranſlate themſelves into their Authors papers, and deprived of their native glories, doe preſent them to the world in their owne deformities; they diſguiſe their beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in thoſe accents they would advance them, as if our language was either too dull or too ſtubborn to expreſſe them, and Eloquence was onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined unto France; nay, ſo delicate is their impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that it attempteth only the choyceſt Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies, and the rareſt of Authors have the leaſure to repent their miſerable Eloquence: but ſuch is
<pb facs="tcp:19251:4"/> the vertue and the happineſſe of learning, that from hence ſhee hath receiv'd incouragements, it being an addition to her glory to be admir'd by all; and being prais'd by Ignorance, from the mouth of her enemy ſhe becomes more fruitfull. The Sunne forbeares not to impart his beames becauſe they draw up clouds, which doe as much obſcure his beauty, as expreſſe his power, and theſe lights of Learning continue ſtill their illuminating influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, though thoſe guilty ſhaddowes doe invade them, and conſcious of the vertue that did attract them, they doe rather forgive then ſuppreſſe their ſplendour. But the workes of this our Author be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as rich in ſubſtance as in beauty, are able to carry their owne ſtrength and light through all the defects of a rude Interpreter; this piece onely of all his Labours lay almoſt forgotten, and hid from obſervation, which being ſet forth by ſo divine a hand, and in ſuch perfect colours, I thought it ſome religion in me to draw the curtaine, and to preſent it to the publike view, wherein if I have ſatisfyed you, it ſhall be new honour unto me, that I have fulfill'd with all the deſire of goodneſſe, which is to communicate her ſelfe, and obeyd her incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations as</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ambitious of your beſt proſperity. Codrington.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:5"/>
            <p>ERrours are all but privations: the Tranſlators ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the Printers haſt, gave theſe leave to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, which their review hath thus called in:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag. 3, lin. 1. for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. 5, lin. 12. for</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed, <hi>r.</hi> inſenſed. <hi>pag. 6, lin. 9. for</hi> the great, <hi>r.</hi> the ſo great. <hi>pag. 8, lin. 2. for</hi> Devill, <hi>r.</hi> Devills. <hi>pag. 14, lin. 25. r.</hi> when addicted. <hi>pag. 15, lin. 25. r.</hi> doe differ. <hi>pag. 16, lin. 25. r.</hi> and tumults. <hi>pag. 19. lin. 15. for <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> r. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. 32, lin. 2. for</hi> another, <hi>r.</hi> the other. <hi>ibid. l. 6. for</hi> thoſe, <hi>r.</hi> theſe. <hi>pag. 35, lin. 2. for</hi> preſſe, <hi>r.</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. <hi>ibid. lin. 1. for</hi> lazy, <hi>r.</hi> dusky. <hi>pag. 55, lin. 6. for</hi> ſquares, <hi>r.</hi> ſquare. <hi>pag. 68, lin 9. for</hi> collect, <hi>r.</hi> draw. <hi>pag. 71, lin. 18. for</hi> le ſpace, <hi>r.</hi> l'eſpace. <hi>lin. 21, for</hi> voire, <hi>r.</hi> voir.</p>
            <p>Lighter faults there are too, which as your eye en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters, are left unto your goodneſſe, either to correct them, or excuſe them.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19251:5"/>
            <head>OF THE KNOWLEDGE <hi>OF GOD.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mong all the viſible Workes of God, Man hath the preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; In man that part is of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt excellence which is called the Soule, for a body is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to us with Beaſts, but a ſoule with Angels.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Now ſeeing there are many faculties of the Soule, that is of greateſt dignity, which is called the Mind or Vnderſtanding; for it gives light un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Will, and ſitting at the Helme doth ſteere and guide the affections, from whence it is called of the Greekes <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the Regent or the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The principall ornament and perfection of this Vnderſtanding is the knowledge of the Truth, which is ſo affected to the Mind as light unto the eye.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19251:6"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But not the knowledge of every Truth makes the Vnderſtanding ſo exact, as the knowledge of thoſe things that are moſt high and perfect; among which, ſince it is not to be expreſt by what a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent diſtance God excells, it evidently follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that the true knowledge of God is the moſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute perfection of the Mind: for ſeeing the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth is the ſame to the Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as light is to the eye, it is evident that by the true knowledge of God the Vnderſtanding is moſt accompliſhed, ſince that God is the Fountaine of Light, the Father of Illuminations, nay Light it ſelfe; in compariſon of whom the ſplendor of the Sunne is neerer darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> But againe, not every knowledge of God doth accompliſh or illuſtrate the Vnderſtanding; but only that which revealed by God himſelfe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in his Word: For as we doe not behold the Sunne in the ſame manner as we doe other things, for other things are diſcerned by the light of the Sunne, but the Sunne illuſtrates himſelfe unto us by his owne light; So God cannnot bee knowne but by his proper Light, and unleſſe he be pleaſed to infuſe into our Soules the true knowledge of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> But before wee ſettle our Meditation on this knowledge of God which is revealed in his Word, it will bee a labour worth the obſervation to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe how farre humane reaſon, having no relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Word of God, can advance it ſelfe; for this is no ſluggiſh Meditation, and from hence
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19251:6"/> great light of rectifyed Reaſon ſhines, from hence great knowledge of Divine wiſedome ſpringeth forth. Before therfore we enter into the Chancell of this Temple, it will be profitable awhile to ſtay in the Courts thereof, where no little ſplendor doth appeare, and where God hath left no obſcure repreſentations of his power and his Wiſedome: for ſo will we aſcend by method and degrees to the Doctrine of the Church, that it may appeare how much the Church doth differ from the <hi>Lycaeum,</hi> how much the Schoole of Chriſt doth excell the Schooles of the Philoſophers, how much the Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>velation of God doth overcome the relation and Capacity of Man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> That in all men there is inherent ſome appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of a God, by experience and the teſtimony of all ages it is manifeſt, among whom there is none ſo wild or barbarous that hath not received ſome forme of Religion, and that eſtabliſhed under moſt grievous puniſhments: for this is not a writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten but a native Law, to which we are not taught, but made, not inſtructed by precepts, but by the principles of Nature; from whence it comes, that in the moſt unreclaimed there is a remorſe of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which ſummons their guilts, and drawes them (though unwilling) to the Tribunall of God, cauſing the prophaneſt wretch to tremble with horrour at the almighty Iudgement; <hi>Suetonius</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth of <hi>Caligula,</hi> that thus hee was heard to threaten <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19251:7"/>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Vnto the Land of Greece will I</l>
               <l>Thee a confined Bond-man tye.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>He would often alſo rehearſe that in <hi>Homer</hi> of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelaus</hi> encountring with <hi>Paris:</hi>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou Father <hi>Iove</hi> of all the Gods</l>
               <l>The moſt pernicious art by ods.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Yet as often as he heard it thunder, he ſought out holes wherein to hide him from his feares, and wakened from ſecurity, ſtartled at the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the revenging God: for every one, as hee is moſt abandoned to vice, ſo at the ſhaking of a leafe, or if
<q>
                  <l>Virides rubum dimovêre Lacertae,</l>
                  <l>Et corde &amp; genibus tremit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>The Lizards greene but move the bramble,</l>
               <l>He in his heart and knees doth tremble.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Hence it is, that we obſerve wicked men, who in the courſe of proſperity had ſhaken off all thought that there was a God, in ſudden dangers to cry out, <hi>O God,</hi> and to fly to his aſſiſtance whom prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they deſpiſed, and ſurely theſe words fall from them unpremeditate, it being an acknowledgement that in ſuddaine apprehenſion of extremities is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from them by victorious Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Nay Idolatry it ſelfe the more abſurd it is, and the more addicted to vaine inventions, the more
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19251:7"/> evidently it declares that there is planted in Man by Nature a knowledge of Divinitie, a knowledge that muſt needs ſit deepe within him, and through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be imprinted; when Man a creature of glory, doth chooſe rather to debaſe himſelfe beneath the beaſts, to worſhip Stocks and Stones; and from his naturall hight of pride to ſubmit himſelfe to the vileſt of things, then to acknowledge at all no deity; neither could they who invented thoſe monſters of gods, haue ever found men ſo prone unto obedience, had they not incountred with minds already incenſed with the perſwaſion of a God, from which perſwaſion there ariſeth an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination to religion.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> Nevertheleſſe, to come to the knowledge of God, the vulgar tread in one path, the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in another, the vulgar rowling his eyes about the Vniverſe with admiration doth contemplate the fixed ſeaſons of the yeare, the beauty and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Sunne, the Ebb and flowing of the Sea, the weight of the Earth hanging in the ayre, and by the becks thereof compacted into a Globe, and balanced with equall weights.
<q>
                  <l>Defectus Solis varios, Lunaeque labores,</l>
                  <l>Vnde tremor terris, qua vi maria alta tumeſcant,</l>
                  <l>Objicibus ruptis, rurſumque in ſeipſa reſidant,</l>
                  <l>Quid tantum Oceano properent ſe tingere Soles,</l>
                  <l>Hiberni, vel quae tardis mora noctibus obſtet.</l>
               </q> The fainting Sun, the Moone in labour oft, (aloft, The Earthquakes birth, what mounts the Deepes</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19251:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19251:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <lg>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:19251:9"/>
               <l>Their barres being broke, calm'd by what powre they runne</l>
               <l>Backe to themſelues; what makes the Winters ſun</l>
               <l>So ſoone into the Ocean diue, What ſtay</l>
               <l>In ſummer keepes the tardy Night away.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> Hee wonders at the perpetuall glidings of the ſtreames, the growth and vertue of the Plants, at the divers formes of living creatures, at their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, their inclinations and inſtincts. Finally at the great perfection of the Vniverſe, that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parts thereof are impediments to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the whole: As in an unfeld Wood, the particular hight of every tree would bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable, were not the whole Forreſt ſeene to be of an equall hight. There is ſcarce therefore any ſo ſtrongly dull, who obſerving theſe will not acknowledge their Author, and value with himſelfe the greatneſſe of the Workeman by the excellence of the Worke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> If any Man ſhould behold a Library well fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, in which the ſhelues are faire, and well ſet up, the books rankt in order, all things are kept neate, and bruſht, and handſome. Is it credible that any man can bee ſo ſottiſh, as to conceiue that this came done by chance, and will not rather im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it to the induſtry of Man: for Confuſion comes by chance, but Order is by Induſtry. But there is no Library ſo aptly digeſted, ſo full, ſo beautifull, that may any wayes compare with the perfection and ſtructure of the fabricke of the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19251:9"/> World. A man may carry in the skirt of his gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a promiſcuous number of Printers Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, which his garment being ſhaken, hee may alſo ſhake and ſcatter on the ground; but will the Characters ſo aptly fall, or will there be ſo fine an induſtry in the Chance, that ſome elegant verſes or neate Oration may be reade? Surely there is no Oration ſo polite, no Verſe compoſed with ſo much art, that may any wayes parallel the Artifice and Beauty of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> This is the firſt way, whereby God affects even barbarous men with ſome touch of divinity, draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even the perverſeſt underſtanding to a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of himſelfe by theſe dumbe Maſters, <hi>Pſal. 19. The Heavens declare the glory of God, and the Firmament ſheweth his handy Workes:</hi> For the inviſible things of him from the creation of the World are clearely ſeene, being underſtood by the things that are made, even his power and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> Adde unto theſe the naturall preſervations and the ſeedes of honeſty and equity, and thoſe pricks of conſcience which gaule even the moſt obdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate with ſecret tortures; for this is a confeſſion of good authority, whereby men profeſſe that they acknowledge a Iudge to whom accounts are to be given, and who doth looke into their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and their actions.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> Neither doe the Devils and malignant Spirits conduce a little to imprint in our minds a deepe perſwaſion that there is a God; for ſeeing it is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19251:10"/> knowen by daily experience, how great and hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full the power of the Devill is, how they raiſe up tempeſts, ſend forth diſeaſes, tranforme men into Wolues, tranſport Groues and Corne (which <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> reporteth to haue happened in the PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VINCE of <hi>Marrucia;</hi>) how they affright men with viſions, and with perplexing Oracles illude thoſe that craue their counſell, and entangle them in errours: Surely mankind expoſed to the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of ſo many inviſible enemies, ſhould haue pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed; nay and the fabricke of the World it ſelfe would haue diſſolv'd, did not theſe Spirits depend on the becke of a ſupreamer power, who bridles their rage, and barres them up in the limits of his eternall Providence.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> Theſe are but obvious and careles obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which fall into the vulgar, even not mindfull of them: But the Philoſophers to the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God haue gone the higher way; for they make them bonds and links with Demonſtrations, by which they ſo chaine the underſtandings, that they draw from them what they will.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> wrote eight bookes of naturall Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy, the ſixe laſt whereof containe no other ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject but of Motion onely and the affections of it: But the laſt doth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> end in the firſt Moover, in him who is immoueable, for ſeeing all things that haue motion are moved by ſome one thing, and that againe by another, and ſo forward: In this chaine of things motionary wee cannot proceed to what is infinite, but wee muſt needs ſtay at one firſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19251:10"/> Moover, who although hee moue all things, is himſelfe immoueable. Even ſo in the body of Man, the joynts are moved by the Arteries, the arteries by the ſinnewes, the ſinnewes by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits animall, the Spirits animall by the Spirits vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, the Spirits vitall by the ſoule, which is not moved but by Accident, or by Another, that is, by the motion of another; as Wiſedome wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in a wiſe man, or as the Governour of a ſhip ſitting at the helme doth ſo reſt, that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the motion of the ſhip hee is moved him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. But if there be any thing that moues it ſelfe, it muſt bee compounded of parts, and one part muſt bee moved of another: But the Firſt Being muſt needs be moſt purely ſimple, and not compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of parts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> Beſides it is eaſie to bee ſeene by evident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that in the order of Efficient cauſes it is impoſſible to proceed unto what is infinite, for if there was no chiefe and primary Cauſe, there would be no ſecond, nor any third Cauſe; and ſo of the reſt, ſo that by this meanes, there would be no Cauſe at all; beſides wee ſhould never arriue unto the laſt effect, for before wee could travaile to it, infinite Cauſes muſt be gone over, now that is infinite which cannot bee gone through, and of which as there is no beginning, ſo there is no ending.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> Neither doe the divers degrees of Goodneſſe and wiſedome (by which Angels are better and wiſer then men, and men themſelues differ among
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19251:11"/> themſelues) availe a little to the knowledge of God and of divine perfection: For this Axiome doth ſtand unſhaken, that qualities (ſuppoſe Heate or Whiteneſſe) are more or leſſe imperfect accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as they are neerer or farther off from the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne degree of perfection, or are diſtant from the chiefe degree of Heate or Whiteneſſe: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong creatures therefore that is the better which commeth moſt neere to the chiefe or primary Goodneſſe; But this Soveraigne Goodneſſe, what is it elſe but God who is Goodneſſe it ſelfe. For as in the order of efficient cauſes, ſo in degrees of Vertue and Perfection, there can be no proceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to what is infinite, but it muſt needs be that there muſt be ſome chiefe and primary Perfection.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> Adde againe to this, what all the World confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that it is impoſſible that any thing ſhould make it ſelfe, for if any thing could make it ſelfe, wee muſt neceſſarily then conclude it, to haue beene, before it was; for to doe, doth preſuppoſe to be: ſince ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the heaven could not forme it ſelfe, it muſt bee formed by ſome one elſe, who muſt truely be both of Soveraigne Power, and of infinite Wiſedome, for to ſo great a worke, he had neither patterne whereby to imitate, no materialls ready wherewith to worke, nor Iourneyman to helpe him. For if theſe had then beene, it would bee againe deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded who had created him, his Matter or his Men, who had indued them with abilities as to ſet for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward God, and helpe him in his worke; So that of neceſſity we muſt ſtay at ſome one, who wanteth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19251:11"/> not the ayde of any, and from whom all things are, who ſeeing that of nothing hee hath made all things, cannot but bee of an Infinite Power, ſince from Nothing to Something, there is an infinite diſproportion; for ſottiſhly profane is that ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous inſolence of the Epicure <hi>Velleius,</hi> who, in the firſt Booke of <hi>Cicero, Of the Nature of the Gods,</hi> deriding the Creation, demandeth what was the foundation, what were the tooles, what were the Leavers, who were the Apprentices, in ſo great a worke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> Beſides the Miſtery of Numbers convinceth plainely, that there was a beginning of the World, and therevpon, that it was created by God, for every Number ariſeth from vnity, when therefore dayes are numbred, it muſt needes bee that there was one firſt Day, and therevpon one firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the heaven, for there is no number infinite in Act, neither can there bee Dayes infinite in number, for if any number were infinite, the number of ten, would infinitely fill vp that infinite number, from whence it would follow, that five would ariſe no oftner then ten, and that one halfe would bee no leſſe then twice as much, nay, in that infinite number there would be as many tennes as vnityes, which ſurely cannot ſtand together, and imply a contradiction.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> Beſides the terme of life and proportions of men ſo much contracted in reſpect of the vigour and the Stature of our forefathers, doe not obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly teſtifie, that there was one firſt Man, and one
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19251:12"/> primary perfection, from which by ſtaires Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue deſcended, for the Diminution of things cannot bee infinite: for ſhould wee runne them over in the Ages paſt vnto Infinitie, wee ſhould at length advance Man vnto a Stature higher then heaven it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> The Scope of all this, is, that by Arguments borrowed from the light of humane Reaſon, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though but clouded and dusky, wee may teach, that as the beames of Light ſhed over all the World doe flow from one beginning, namely the Sunne, and as Numbers proceede all from vnity, and in the body of Man as all the Arteryes and Vitall facultyes, proceede from one heart, ſo every Being doth depend and is ſuſtained by one Chiefe and Soveraigne Beeing, who ſhould hee withold, or but withdraw his Vertue, and his Influence, All things preſently would diſſolue and returne into their ancient Nothing; No otherwiſe than if the Sunne being taken from vs, whatſoever there is of Light would bee turned into Darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> Now if any ſhould demand what moved God to put his hand vnto this Worke, the anſwer is ready, For God made all things for himſelfe, and was mooued with no other conſideration than with his owne Loue: For God is not onely the efficient Cauſe of all things but the finall alſo as the Apoſtle witneſſeth in the ſecond of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, where hee alledgeth, that God is for whom and by whom all things are: All things are for God, as hee is the End of all things and moſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19251:12"/> Good; all things are by God, as hee is the efficient Cauſe of all things and moſt great: Deſeruedly therefore doe wee title God Moſt Good, Moſt Great, but firſt moſt Good, before moſt Great: for hee is moſt Good as hee is the End, for the End is alwayes the foremoſt in the Intention, and the Efficient Cauſe is but mooued by it. Seeing therefore there is no Reaſonable or Intellectuall Agent which vndertaketh any thing without pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing to himſelfe the End which ever appeareth Good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the moſt chiefe and Soveraigne AGENT could not worke; but for the laſt and beſt End, And ſeeing there is nothing better then God, nay, Seeing all things whatſoever are Good come from God, God could not worke for any other End but for himſelfe; And ſeeing there is nothing that ſhould bee rather pourtrayed or repreſented in a picture, then what doth ſeeme moſt beautifull, God who is the firſt Beauty, and the firſt Light, was pleas'd to draw his owne Picture, and as in <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias</hi> his <hi>Minerva,</hi> the Artiſt himſelfe hath imprinted in his worke, an vndefac'd reſemblance of himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> But ſeeing now of things created, part are Bodies part are Spirits and immateriall Subſtances, among the Spirits the Angels are moſt eminent, next vnto which are the Soules of Men, among the Bodyes the firſt Heaven is aboue all moſt honourable; Wherefore when God in all his creatures hath imprinted ſome tracks of his power and his wiſedome, the Spirits by a more ſpeciall priviledge have ingraven in them the image of himſelfe, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19251:13"/> that not drawne by a pencil as Painters vſe, expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing onely Colours and proportions, but ſuch an image, as is beheld in a Glaſſe, which repreſents euen our motions and our Actions; For God hath powred into Spirits the Light of vnderſtanding, and knowledge of the Truth, which is as a certaine ſparke of the Diuine Light, hee hath adorned their Wills (whoſe faculty it is to mooue and produce Actions) with Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe, hee hath conferred on them Immortality and a liberty of choyce, which are the Lineaments of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Image, and Reſemblances of God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> Which image of God as it is the moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ornament of the Intellctuall creature, ſo there is nothing more vgly than the deformation of it, which is occaſioned, when the Soule, the eye of the vnderſtanding beeing pulled out by Ignorance, and the lineaments of this Image beeing ſoiled by Vice, is turned into a Monſter, and beeing hated by God hath rendred it ſelfe ſo miſerable by its owne default, that it is not any wayes worthy of the Mercy of God; For as the Image of a King ſtampt on ſiluer, with much rubbing and often fret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt the Ground becomes defaced, ſo in our ſoules, the image of God is deformed, addicted to earthly things, and as it were wallowed in the mire, they are turn'd away from divine contemplation, and from the Love of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> Nay, and in the firſt body too (which is heaven) God hath imprinted certaine tokens, I had almoſt ſayd a certaine Image of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19251:13"/> For God hath turned it into a roundneſſe, an imitation of his diuine infiniteneſſe, becauſe this figure hath neither beginning nor ending, and in the ſame firſt Body hee hath engraven no obſcure reſemblances of his immobility and eternall Reſt, a reſt which is yet notwithſtanding in continuall motion; For although the Heaven is continually mooved by Parts, while one Part doth ſucceede another, ſo it is, that the whole Body reſteth, neither is it mooved from its place; Hee hath alſo placed in the heavens an imitation of his Power, diſpoſing of his Worke in ſuch a method, that the elementary bodyes are governed by the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly, and ſuperiour bodyes worke into the inferiour their powerfull influences, And indeed moſt true is that of Ariſtotle in his ſecond Booke <hi>de Gen. Cap.</hi> 10. That the perpetuall durance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of things ought to be imputed to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple &amp; daily motion of the Sun from the Eaſt into the Weſt; But that Generation and corruption doth ariſe from the oblique Courſes of the Sun and Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets through the Zodiack, whiles acording to their Situation they change their Aſpects, and by their acceſſe neerer to vs, or receſſe farther from vs, the affections and Qualities of things differ.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> That this Heaven is the palace of the Almighty, not onely the ſacred Word, but the conſtant opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all Nations juſtifies; For though the Eſſence of God filleth all things, and is not circumſcribed by any limits, yet by nature it is ingrafted in man in meditation and holy excerciſes to remooue his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19251:14"/> mind, what in him lyes, from earthly things, and to advance it vnto heaven; Wherefore wee pray vnto God with knees humbled to the Earth, but with eyes lift vp to heaven, the one of which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth our humility, the other teſtifieth our Hope, the one abates our pride, the other doth ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance our thoughts. Neither without good Cauſe hath humane Reaſon placed the throne of God in Heaven, For what more convenient habitation can there bee for God that mooveth all things, then that Body, by which hee mooueth all things? What fitter ſeate can there be for the Father of Lights, then that Region illuſtrious of it ſelfe, and allwayes ſhining with its natiue ſplendor? what more agreeable to the Nature of God, who is the God of Peace, and not ſubject vnto change, then there to haue his throne, where is everlaſting Peace, vntroubled reſt, nor ſigne of Change; Hence it is as <hi>Iuſtinus</hi> obſerves, in his Exhortation to the Greekes, that <hi>Iupiter</hi> in <hi>Homer</hi> tooke <hi>Ate</hi> or Diſcord by the haires of the head, and threw her headlong downe from heaven, who fell on this lower Region, which is ſhaken with Winds, with tempeſts, and with Earthquakes, where there reignes Warre, Tumult, and Rebellion againſt God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> By theſe ſtaires, as it were, the mind of Man aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cends to the knowledge of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by this wing ſhee doth mount her ſelfe: Theſe are thoſe backe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> parts of the Almighty which it is permitted to Man to ſee, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. to wit, the workes of God
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19251:14"/> which are knowen to us onely <hi>ex poſteriori</hi> by the events and the effects: Or rather by this doth not the Scripture giue us to underſtand, that God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming cannot be perceived, but after that hee hath paſſed by and ſtrooke us, then we know him: For wee are altogether ignorant what God will doe; but after the execution of the Act, then wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his power either by afflicting or deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering us.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> Neither doth our Intention levell our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to proue that there is a God whom the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils themſelues acknowledge, whom who denies he deſerues rather the Executioner to torment him, then the Philoſopher to inſtruct him; but theſe things are brought forth to ſhew, on what weake rods Mans reaſon leaning hath yet upheld it ſelfe, and ſtrengthned that glimmering light which it had by Nature concerning the Divinity; and how although imperfectly it hath arrived to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of a God: As alſo to expound that which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Act. 14. That God never left him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe without witneſſe,</hi> which may be underſtood not onely of outward teſtimonies ſuch as are raine and fruitfull ſeaſons, but may alſo be extended as well to the inward teſtimony of every Conſcience, as the outward teſtimony of the Creatures.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> Neither by this doe I inferre that this Aſſertion that THERE IS A GOD, is of the number of thoſe which are knowen by their owne Nature. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the ſecond of the <hi>Poſteriors</hi> text 6. ſaith, that thoſe Enuntiations are knowen by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19251:15"/> which are no ſooner underſtood but they are beleeved: As who underſtands what the WHOLE is, and what a PART is, hee cannot but know and beleeue that the whole is more then the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: Neither can a man perſwade himſelfe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the contrary; but this Aſſertion that THERE IS A GOD is not of that Nature; For after the termes are underſtood there are found of thoſe that dare deny him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> Although I beleeue they are but few in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, yet every Age hath encounterd with many others, who for all they acknowledge that there is a God, doe yet deny his Providence; for this opinion is moſt flatter'd and ſtroakd by vices, and is moſt apt of all to unbutton to Intemperance; but of thoſe that haue altogether denyed God, you ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll ſcarce find any one in any one Age: It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt indeed that <hi>Diagoras Melius</hi> was accuſed of Atheiſme, not that hee denyed that there was a God, but that hee deſpiſed the counterfeit Gods of the Athenians, and their empty ſuperſtitions; this is he, that taking the wooden Statue of <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les</hi> by the legge threw it into the fire, thus up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brayding it: <hi>This</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>ſhall bee thy thirteenth labour;</hi> and <hi>Clemens Alexandrinus</hi> in his booke in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled <hi>Protrepticon</hi> doth affirme, that the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion is to bee had of <hi>Theodorus</hi> the Syrenian, <hi>Evo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merus, Hippone, Nicanor,</hi> which were all accounted Atheiſts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> Hitherto therefore humane Reaſon hath not unhappily diſputed, for by the Conduct of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19251:15"/> and aſſiſtance of Philoſophy it hath come ſo farre as to affirme that there is a God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> But when they come to deſcribe the Nature of God, and endeavour themſelves to ſatisfy the Queſtion, wherein it is demanded what God is, a huge and thicke miſt of ignorance doth over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread and cloud the ſenſe, and the light of God himſelfe, turnd into darkneſſe, doth ſtrike the Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding with blindneſſe and aſtoniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> Some there are, as <hi>Plato, Cicero,</hi> and <hi>Virgil Aen.</hi> 6. who have thought that God is the Soule of the world, who doth ſo moove and guide it, as the ſoule doth the body; Others have affirmed God to bee whatſoever is. That of <hi>Euripides</hi> is well knowne.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <lg>
               <l>Seeſt thou the Aires uncompaſt height about,</l>
               <l>Seeſt thou the greatnes of the Earth throughout,</l>
               <l>And what ſhe doth in watry armes incloſe,</l>
               <l>Count all that God, and doe it <hi>Iove</hi> ſuppoſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> There have beene of them who have affirmed that God is a Circle, whoſe center is every where, and Circumference no where: It is commonly reported how by long procraſtinations <hi>Simonides</hi> deluded the demands of <hi>Hiero,</hi> who deſired to know what God was, craving at firſt the liberty of one day to reſolve him, then two dayes, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards three, daily augmenting the number, always acknowledging his inability to anſwer the requeſt,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19251:16"/> and that the more hee conſidered what God was, the more the difficulties did ariſe and multiply.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> The Iewes that they might ſhew the Eſſence of God to be inexplicable, they would have the name of God unutterable, and which neither could nor ought to be pronounc'd by man, which the Angell who is alſo called God, who wraſtled with <hi>Iacob,</hi> ſeemes to imply: for <hi>Iacob</hi> defiring him to declare his Name, he refus'd it, ſaying, <hi>Wherfore is it that thou doſt aske after my name?</hi> So the Angel who is called God alſo, <hi>Iud.</hi> 13. checked the curioſity of <hi>Manoah,</hi> who deſired to know what his name was, in theſe words, <hi>Wherefore askeſt thou after my name, ſeeing it is wonderfull?</hi> In Hebrew bookes, even to this day, the name of God is written <hi>Iehovah,</hi> which name it ſeemes was wrote on purpoſe by the Rabbins, that the name of God which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten on the front of the Miter might bee hidden: For <hi>Ioſephus,</hi> who was both a Prieſt and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, doth teſtify in the ſixth booke of the Iewes warres, that the Name praefixed on the Miter of the Prieſthood had foure vowels, whereby it doth plainely appeare that this name was not <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hova,</hi> but <hi>IOVA,</hi> by pronouncing <hi>I</hi> and <hi>V</hi> not like Conſonants, but diſtinctly by themſelves as they are Vowells: which the word <hi>Iove</hi> among the Heathens doth alſo intimate: nor much diverſe from this is <hi>Diodorus</hi> the Sicilian, who in the firſt Booke of his Hiſtoricall Library doth affirme that the God of <hi>Moſes</hi> was called ΙΑΩ. But <hi>Clemens A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrinus</hi> in the fifth Booke <hi>Stromat. pag.</hi> 240,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19251:16"/> doth ſay that the foure-lettered name which was writ about the Sacerdotiall Tyare was ΙΑΟΤ, which word conſiſts of the ſame vowels, as the word ΙΟΤΑ, although the letters are otherwiſe diſpoſed: but howſoever it was, they are as wide from truth as Heaven, that thinke by this word, or any other, the Eſſence of God can be expreſt; for no name can bee given which can expreſſe the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Man, nay of a ſtone, ſeeing there are no names eſſential, but names are given unto things by common inſtitution, and as pleaſed thoſe who firſt did practiſe the diverſity of tongues to impoſe upon them: thoſe names only expreſſe the Eſſence of the things they ſignify, which doe imitate their ſounds, as the creaking of the Crow, the lowing of the Bullocke.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> But the Eſſence of God, as it cannot be expreſt by words, ſo it cannot be conceiv'd by the Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, the cauſes of which are many; for a thing infinite cannot be comprehended by a thing finite, and the inacceſſible light of God doth dazle the Vnderſtanding. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> confeſſing in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of his Metaphyſicks, that as the eyes of Owles cannot endure the beames and ſplendor of the Sunne, ſo the edges of our Vnderſtanding doe rebate themſelves in the apprehenſions of the primary Beings: The ſame Philoſopher affirmes, that there is nothing in the Vnderſtanding that was not firſt in the ſenſe: but God cannot be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the ſenſe. Againe, as long as Vnderſtanding is in the body, it comprehendeth nothing but by
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19251:17"/> the helpe of the Fancie, and in the act of Vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it turneth to the Fancie, a fancie which doth as much annoy, as helpe the Vnderſtanding whiles it repreſenteth God cloath'd in the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Nature, as of quantities, of extenſion of parts, and many other accidents. Againe, every punie knowes that things are defined by their <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> and their <hi>difference,</hi> or if that they bee not at hand they are then defined by their <hi>proper Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents:</hi> But of God there is no <hi>Genus,</hi> no <hi>ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call difference,</hi> no <hi>Accident</hi> at all, ſince God is all ſubſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> To theſe Inconveniences and impediments in attayning to the Knowledge of God, there is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not onely Mans ſlowneſſe and infirmity, but his perverſeneſſe and neglect: For many are called from this ſtudy by the ſloth and dulneſſe of their wit, rebating it ſelfe in the contemplation of heavenly things; ſome are taken from it by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke or private affaires, which call downe to earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things the mounting endeavours of the mind, and (as I may ſo ſay) doe pull the wings of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation; and many, the ſlaves of pleaſure, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to their belly, miſpriſe the ſtudy of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as a thing they have no need of; nay, as it were ſome trifling importunity, ſome light or empty Meteor.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> And of thoſe who apply their underſtandings to the knowledge of God, there are but few that perſevere in the right courſe, but either they fall off from their deſigne, or ſtrucken with a giddi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19251:17"/> doe ſtumble on the threſhold, or turning aſide to vaine delights, doe wrap themſelues in errors; from hence ariſe thoſe monſters of the Gods, and illuding Vizards which were worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped by the Heathen, who wanting an able Maſter to inſtruct them did follow the cuſtome of their Countrey, which commanded them to adore the peculiar Gods of their countrey or their family, thinking it would bee better with them if every particular man ſhould chooſe him a private and particular God: From this ſprang up ſuch a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Gods, that in <hi>Heſiods</hi> time they amounted to the number of thirty thouſand: Againe it is planted in Men, which is their great folly, to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure God by themſelves, &amp; to cloth him not only with mans figure but with his affections alſo; they doe not thinke that they ſerue God aright, unleſſe they make him like a Man or Beaſt, that they may haue before them ſome preſent object, on which they might ſettle their eyes and their devotion; This was the language of the Iſraelites to <hi>Aaron, Make us gods which ſhall goe before us, Exod.</hi> 32. And becauſe God had made Man to the Image of God; Man againe to require the courteſie would make God to the Image of Man: By which God after they had diſcharged themſelues of ſome Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to him, they conceited themſelues not onely ſafe againſt all ſins already committed, but thought for the time to come, they had got a licence and a priviledge to ſinne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> For theſe cauſes there haue not beene wanting
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19251:18"/> ſome, who turning deſperation into cenſure, haue beene of judgement that God could not be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, and that in vaine they travaile that beſtow their labours in ſearching out his Nature, whoſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty indeed deſerues to bee excuſed, were there not too much of ſloth in it, and were not the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of his knowledge an occaſion of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of his loue, and by the ſame contempt whereby the knowledge of the Divine Nature is neglected, the knowledge alſo of the Divine Will would be deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> 
               <hi>Plato</hi> in whoſe tracks <hi>Cicero</hi> treads, hath beene more happy in this inquiry, for hee hath delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the world many true and excellent things concerning God; as when he ſaith, <hi>That he is the Author and Governour of all things, moſt Good, moſt Great, who ſeeth and ſuſtaineth all things, and that the life of a wiſe man is nothing elſe but a returne to God, and that the way to God is by the ſtudy of Piety and Iuſtice:</hi> This and much more to this purpoſe, wee may reade in <hi>Platoes Politicon, his Philebus, Theate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> and <hi>Timaeus,</hi> where we may find many things taken from the Ancient Divinity which he had learned in Egypt and in Siria.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> 
               <hi>Aristotle</hi> more ſharpe in underſtanding, doth adde, that God is the firſt Moover, the firſt Being, and moving Power; who notwithſtanding is unmoueable, to whom as to their End the Caeleſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Intelligences perpetually mooue, and that he is the cauſe of the continuall Motions of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, which cauſeth other Motions, and from
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19251:18"/> whom the inferiour bodies receiue their influences.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> For although to ſee into the myſteries of God, and to know his Eſſence is not granted unto any Creature, no not unto the Angels, becauſe there is no proportion betwixt a finite faculty and an infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite object, yet thoſe holy inſtructions are not to bee neglected, which preſent themſelues unto the creature concerning God, or which the power of the underſtanding hath attained by meditation, neither are the naturall Sparkes of the knowledge of God to be ſmotherd in us, but to be awakened and blowen up, that from them our loue to God might be inflamed; For we loue not things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, but from the knowledge of good, the loue and deſire of enjoying it doth increaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/> And although there be no <hi>Genus</hi> of God that is Synonimall, or fully able to define him; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be no ſpecificall difference, yet there is a <hi>Genus</hi> which is called Analogicall, and a Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence too; although but by way of Negation; as when wee ſay that a Beaſt is a creature that is <hi>not</hi> reaſonable, both which <hi>Genus</hi> and which Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence being apprehended by the underſtanding as proper Qualities doe conduct our minds unto ſome knowledge of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/> I am of opinion, moſt aptly and as farre as Mans capacitie is able to conceiue that God may be thus defined, <hi>God is the firſt, the moſt chiefe, and moſt perfect Being, from whom there floweth and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth all Entity and Perfection:</hi> For other things which are his Attributes, as his Eternity,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19251:19"/> his Simplicity, his Wiſedome, and of like Nature are all contayned under this word of chiefe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/> I ſay that not onely every Being proceeds from God, but every Entity doth ever and altogether depend on him: for God doth giue unto his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures both their Being and their life, after the ſame manner as the Sun doth communicate his beames, which doe ſo flow from him, as they are alwayes depending on him; who, ſhould he but a little hide his face, incontinently the Light would ceaſe, and his beames vaniſh away; which the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> doth imply, <hi>If thou hideſt thy face they are troubled, if thou takeſt away their breath they dye, and returne unto their duſt: Pſal.</hi> 104.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="49"/> Moreover, although wee cannot in mind con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, or in words expreſſe the divine perfection; nevertheleſſe wee may after a manner ſhaddow it forth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> This word Perfect is taken many wayes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a Worke is ſaid to be perfect when it is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed or accompliſhed; as a houſe where the Workeman hath no more worke to doe, or a booke to which the Author hath put his laſt hand; God is not ſaid to be perfect in this manner, for this perfection proceeds to perfection from imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, of which there never any was in God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/> That alſo is ſaid to be perfect, that wanteth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing by which it may attaine the end to which it was ordained: In which ſenſe all the workes of God are in their kinds perfect; and <hi>Momus</hi> himſelfe
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19251:19"/> can find nothing in them, that he might taxe either for exceſſe or for default; neither is God ſaid to be perfect after this manner, for he is not ordained to any particular end, who is himſelfe the chiefe End of all things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/> But ſo wee doe ſay God is perfect, as no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is wanting to him; for every thing is ſaid to bee imperfect which is <hi>in potentiâ paſsiuâ,</hi> in a paſſiue power to ſome Act; but God is a pure Act, and in him there is no power that is paſſiue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/> Wherefore it muſt needs enſue, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perfection and vertue there is in the creatures, it muſt not onely flow from that primary perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which is in God, but muſt alſo bee included in it; For as the reaſonable ſoule comprehends the vertues of the ſoule Senſitiue, and Vegetatiue, and all the power of inferior Magiſtrates is included in the power of the Prince, and as humane Diſcourſe is contained in the Angelicall Intellect; ſo all the perfections of the Creatures are incloſed in the perfection of the Creator.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> But thoſe Perfections of the Creatures are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted which are either the remedies of euills or the Helps and Aydes of Imperfections, for to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſuch perfections to God is rather a reproach then Praiſe (as for example) The motionary facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty whereby the liuing Creature mooues it ſelfe by a locall Motion, is a perfection in the Creature which is not a perfection in God, becauſe this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is but the crutch of imperfection, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Creature cannot bee in the ſame time in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19251:20"/> many places the motionary faculty is given to him, which in ſome ſort doth remedy this imperfection, for by it ſucceſſiuely at leaſt, and in diuerſe times, the creature may bee in diuerſe places; This per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection muſt not bee look'd for in God, for ſeeing hee is every where, there is no place for him to mooue vnto.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> So to diſcourſe and frame a Sillogiſme is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection indued by God into the mind of Man, a ſearchereſſe out of Truth, and by things more knowen working out a Way to things vnknowne; this perfection ſeing it is the remedy of Ignorance and a helpe vnto our weakeneſſe, it would bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane to look for it in God, who diſputeth not, nor makes it his labor to find out the truth, nor collect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth one thing by another, for all things are knowen to him alike, and hee vnderſtandeth all things in one pure and ſimple thought, there is no need that God ſhould turn the eye of his Vnderſtanding to thoſe things which hee would know, for he but beholds himſelfe and finds in his owne mind the eternall Modell of all things, and in his will the efficient Cauſe of all Events; And as a man that had his whole body beſet with eyes, or was all one eye had no need to turne his body or his eyes to behold the things that are about him, for in one and the ſame point of time, whitherſoever hee caſts his eye, all objects round about him preſent themſelues vnto him with an equall viewe, ſo ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that one thing cannot bee more preſent to God then another, there is no need that he ſhould turne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19251:20"/> about the eye of his vnderſtanding, or behold things in a ſucceſſion of order, or ſhould bring a new intention of the mind to attaine new know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, for there is not any thing that is or can bee new vnto him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/> So the memory of things paſt, and foreſight of things to come are the Vertues and Perfections of a Man that is borne in time, and whoſe Actions and Duration are meaſured by time, which vertues God hath endowed him with, that hee might pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the inſtructions receiued and eſchew things hurtfull; Theſe perfections (ſeeing they are the remedies of Imperfections and the aydes of our Infirmities) cannot bee attributed to God, but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>properly; and what in this Subject wee attribute to God which belongs to man, it muſt bee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood in a ſenſe moſt agreeable to the Majeſtie of God, for neither the memory of things paſt, nor the conjecture of things to come, can bee ſaid to bee in God becauſe all things are preſent to him; the maker of Time, is before time and above it, neither is his duration meaſured by it; for as the Infiniteneſſe of God doth not onely conſiſt in this that hee is not circumſcrib'd by limits, but moſt eſpecially in this, that hee is all in every place; ſo his eternity likewiſe is not placed in this onely, that hee is without beginning and without end, but rather in this, that his life is not a Courſe of Motions as ours, but a perpetuall Reſt, and in which there is no ſucceſſion of Parts, for otherwiſe hee ſhould dayly looſe a part or portion of his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19251:21"/> life, but hee enjoyes all his life and perfection, together, and in a Moment: for Aeternity, as <hi>Boetius</hi> doth define it, is the whole, together, and the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect poſſeſſion of a life vnlimited. And as to a Man ſitting on the banke of a River, onely that Water is preſent to him which is obſerved by him in that inſtant Moment and point of time, but that part of the River is not preſented to his eyes which is not yet come to them or but now gone from them, yet the ſame Man, were hee exalted into the vpper region of the ayre, might behold the whole River, and at one view obſerue both the fountaine and the courſes of it; So by the eye of God who is above time, together, and in a moment, is obſerued the whole flux of tranſitory things, neither in him is there addition or ſubtraction, for all things that are, are preſent to him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/> There is another difference and that too a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable one, for theſe perfections which are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and ſcattered in the creatures, in God are one and the ſame perfection; As if there were a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which could excerciſe all thoſe faculties by one ſenſe, which wee doe by five: And as all lines drawen from the circumference to the Center of the Circle are vnited in the Centers point, and the farther they are from the Center the more they ſcatter and enlarge themſelues; ſo all the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which are diſpenſed among the Creatures are collected in God into one Vertue, and the farther they depart from God, the more ſcattered &amp; thin they doe appeare, till at length they degenerate into the vileſt of vices.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:19251:21"/>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> The Cauſe of this difference is, that theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and vertues of the creatures are Qualities and ornaments added to their Subſtances, but the onely perfection of God is the Eſſence of God himſelfe, which though it be moſt pure, yet becauſe it hath diverſe effects, it hath diverſe names; In Man indeede it is one thing to know, and another thing to Will, neither is the foreknowledge of Man the cauſe of the event to come, But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the foreknowledge of God is the very Eſſence of him, it is neceſſary that it muſt bee the ſame perfection with his Will and Providence, and that in his foreknowledge hee hath a power not onely foreſeeing but alſo diſpoſing of things to come; Neither muſt we thinke that God foreſees ſtormes to come, or Earthquakes, or Ecclipſes, becauſe they are to come, but wee muſt rather ſay, that they will come becauſe that God foreſees them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/> Neither would I by this inferre, that if at any time the ſame perfections bee attributed to God and to the Creatures, that the ſame perfections are equall in the Creatures as in God, Wiſedome and Righteouſneſſe are not attributed to the Angells as to God, in one and the ſame Senſe, for in God they are Subſtances, but in Angels Qualities, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can theſe bee ſaid to bee termes equivocall, that is words of the ſame ſound, for words purely equivocall (ſuch as the word <hi>Lupus</hi> in Latine, which ſignifieth the creature of prey and Rapine, as alſo the bitte or ſnaffle of a bridle) hold no intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence together, neither haue they any order in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19251:22"/> neither by one doe we proceed to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of another; but the wiſdome and the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe of Angells are reſemblances of the diuine Righteouſneſſe and ſparks ſhining from it, and the knowledge of one doth advance our ſpirits to the Contemplation of another; Thoſe things there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may bee ſaid to haue an Analogicall reference which are as <hi>Ens,</hi> or Being, which is in Logick called the <hi>Genus Analogum</hi> of Subſtances and Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, and ſo a foote is ſpoken either by the foote of a liuing creature or by the treſsle of a bed or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for in the greateſt diuerſity there is no little Analogy or Reſemblance.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> Whoſoever therefore will exalt his thoughts without danger to the contemplation of the Diuine perfection, muſt runne over in his owne Mind all the perfections that are in a Creature, and abſtract and ſever from him whatſoever ther is of Imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and alſo thoſe perfections which are the helps and Crutches of Imperfections, all theſe being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, that which remaineth will bee GOD; As, from Man to whom God hath given, to bee, to liue, to vnderſtand, take away but theſe things, To bee a Body, to haue a Beginning, to bee cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribed by Limits, to bee compounded of Parts, to bee the Subject of Accidents, to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued from one place to another, to diſcourſe, to remember, to forget, to learne, to bee ignorant, to bee able to ſinne, to depend on a Superiour Beeing, and ſuch like, theſe things taken away, that which remaineth will bee GOD, namely a
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19251:22"/> liuing Beeing, vnderſtanding, incorporeall, without beginning, not depending on another, infinite, ſimple, vnchangeable, vnmooveable, all-knowing, perfectly Iuſt, and perfectly Wiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> Moreover, although wee cannot demonſtrate what God is by any thing that is precedent, for ſubſtances are not the Subjects of Demonſtrations, or graunt they were, yet the Eſſence of God muſt bee exempted, becauſe no Cauſe can bee rendred of it; howſoever (I ſpeake after the manner of men) ſome of the divine Attributes are demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrated by what goes before, while one Attribute is deduced from another by a neceſſary Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; ſo, out of the Infiniteneſſe of God, his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mobility is demonſtrated, for whither can hee mooue himſelfe who is every where? and in the ſame manner from the Simplicity of the Eſſence of God, wee may deduce his incorruptibility, for all corruption doth proceede from the diſſolution of the Compound; Nay, from the ſame ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Gods eſſence, wee doe neceſſarily inferre that in God there are no Accidents, for hee were not moſt pure and Simple, if hee did conſiſt of Subſtance and of Accidents; then againe, from the omniſcience of God is collected the vnchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe of his decrees, For then Men doe change their reſolutions and fall off from their enterpriſes, when any thing doth happen vnthought of, or vnlook'd for.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/> The vnderſtanding of man Mounted on theſe wings, can exalt her ſelfe to ſome knowledge of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19251:23"/> the Divine Nature, by which preexercitations the Mind being ſtirred vp doth more greedily receiue, and more eaſily digeſt the Inſtructions reveiled in the Word of God, which excellent and ſublimed knowledge of the Word of God, ſhall bee now the Subject of our Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> God therefore who with a courſer pencill hath ſhaddowed himſelfe in his creatures, hath expreſt himſelfe in his Word in more bright and liuely Colours, and that two wayes; For there is one knowledge of God which is deliuered in his law, and another which is contained in the Goſpell, which two knowledges doe anſwer the two trees which God firſt planted in Paradiſe, whereof one gaue the knowledge of Good and Euill which is the office of the Law, the other doth beare the fruit of Life which is the benefit of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> For wee haue three wayes of knowing God, one by the workes of God, the ſecond by the Law, the third by the Goſpell, among which the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge by the Goſpell is farre moſt excellent, for the other two knowledges preſent God to our vnderſtandings, as a Creator, a Lord, and as the Maſter of our life, but this as a father and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; The two former knowledges of God doe teach what God is in himſelfe, but this latter what God will bee towards vs, the former doe ſtrike feare and wonder into vs, the latter advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth Hope and createth Love: ſo that without the knowledge of God by the Goſpell, the knowledge
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:19251:23"/> of him by his workes is but a lazy ſpeculation, and the preſſe of him by the law is terrible, and doth preſſe our Conſciences with a burden vnſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/> It ſeemed not enough therefore to God, to teach us by his creatures, who in throngs as it were and by admirable conſent giue teſtimony of him, but hee hath unlocked his ſacred mouth, that by his word hee might endue us with the knowledge of himſelfe, and by that knowledge inflame our loues.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/> For by the Architecture of the world, the Power and the Wiſedome of God is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged but not his Iuſtice, nor his Mercy, without the knowledge of which there is no ſalvation; alſo the works of God doe witneſſe the greatneſſe of the Workeman, but they lay not open unto us his will, nor deliver in what manner he is to bee worſhipped: Beſides, when the contemplation of the creatures doth repreſent God unto us, as hee is armed with thunders and ſhaking heaven and earth but with the turning of his eye, this contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doth affect us with aſtoniſhment, with the feare and horrour of an Armed Iudge, were there not another doctrine which doth appeaſe our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and giue unto us aſſurances of the loue of God, for then doe wee with filiall eyes behold heaven as the portall of our fathers Palace, when God in his word hath given to us the evident teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of his paternall loue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> Moreover, wee ſhould grow darke in the very
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19251:24"/> contemplation of the workes of God, did we not diſtinctly ſee them by the word as through ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, which of themſelues would hardly be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; this doth the Apoſtle teach us in the 11. <hi>Heb. Through faith wee underſtand that the worlds were fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the word of God, ſo that things which are ſeene were not made of things which doe appeare;</hi> giving us to underſtand, that they onely beleeue, as they ought, the creation of the world to be without any praeexiſtent matter, which receiue the word of God with the obedience of faith; would you haue it made legible by examples? The hiſtory of the Creation is well knowen as it is related by <hi>Moſes</hi> in the beginning of <hi>Geneſis:</hi> It is there declared that the Sunne was created but in the fourth day; ſo that three dayes and as many nights were paſt when the Sunne was firſt created; this being to informe us that God did ſo uſe the Sunne to illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the world, that yet without it and before it, hee ſhined into the world by his owne light, being no wayes obliged to ſecond cauſes; And when <hi>Moſes</hi> aſſigneth a beginning and ending to every day, in theſe words, <hi>And the Evening and the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning were the firſt day,</hi> and ſo of the other dayes, onely in the ſeventh day <hi>Moſes</hi> maketh no mention of the Evening, for the Reſt of the ſeventh day is the ſhadow and the figure of the heavenly and eternall Reſt of which there is no End; ſo when the Naturaliſts report many things of the Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow, the onely end and ſignification of the Raine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow can be learned out of the word of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19251:24"/> how many myſteries and inſtructions doth the Creation of Man and Woman containe? Surely God forming the body of Man out of clay, did conforme his mind alſo to humility, and a religious lowlineſſe by remembring him of his diſcent and ignoble parentage; alſo when God created a Wife for the man when he was aſleepe, it doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct us, that a good Wife is not obtayned by a mans owne induſtry or wiſedome, but by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, which doth bring her to him while hee is aſleepe: Againe, the creation of the Woman from the part moſt neere unto the heart, what doth it imply? but faith and loue: and that I may not diue into hidden myſteries, and by what meanes <hi>Adam</hi> overcome with a deepe ſleepe, (which is called by <hi>Homer</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the brother of Death) was a figure of Chriſt in the ſleepe of Death, which ſleepe God made uſe of to raiſe unto him his Spouſe which is the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/> And truely a Spirit that is exerciſed in the word of God, will receiue much fruite and pleaſure from the contemplation of the creatures: For beſides, that hee beholds the fields<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the woods, and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever elſe is pleaſant on earth as the poſſeſſions of his father, and doth walke in them as in his owne inheritance, and gathers thoſe fruits which hee knowes by right are his, as being created for the uſe of the Sonnes of God, there is this addition more, that hee cannot beſtow his eyes on any place wherein a reſemblance of vertue ſhall not encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them, and refreſh his memory with ſomething
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19251:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:19251:25"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19251:26"/> which hee hath heard or read in the word of God: If a godly man and one that knowes God by his word, beholds a fountaine of running waters, they wil preſently prompt his memory to the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of life, in <hi>Iohn 4. And to the waters ſpringing up to everlaſting life:</hi> If he beholds the Sunne he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templates how greater farre is the Light of the Sun of Righteouſneſſe: If he conſiders the viciſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the dayes and nights he comforts himſelfe in the remembrance of the aſſurance of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God, God himſelfe ſo ſpeaking by the mouth of <hi>Ieremy: If you can breake my Covenant of the day and my Covenant of the night, &amp; that there ſhould not be Day and Night in their ſeaſon, then ſhall you alſo be able to breake my Covenant with David:</hi> If he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds a Shepheard driving of his flocke, hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>members preſently that in the <hi>Pſalme; The Lord is my Shepheard I ſhall not want:</hi> Finally, whereſoever hee turnes his eye hee will find an ample ſubject of prayſe and of thankeſgiving, and a wide field will be opened for holy meditation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> That which we ſpeake of the workes of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is to be vnderſtood alſo of the workes of Gubernation and of the divine Providence, the effects of which, man is not able to diſcerne, unleſſe he annoynt his eyes with the ſalve of Gods word, and wipe the filmes from off them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> There are not wanting examples among the Heathens, who being oppreſt by calamities, have acknowledged God the revenger of their offences, or freed from evills have aſcribed to him the praiſe
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19251:26"/> of their deliverance. Moſt remarkable is that of <hi>Sethon</hi> King of Aegypt, who holding a Mouſe in his hand, ſtood cut in ſtone in the Temple of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> on his Statue was inſcribed.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</q>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſoever lookes on mee,</l>
               <l>Let him godly learne to be.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Giving thankes to God, who by multitudes of Mice ſent in among them had disbanded the army of <hi>Sennacherib</hi> the King of the Aſſyrians. And <hi>Phlegas</hi> in the ſixt of the <hi>Aeneids,</hi> among a thouſand torments, in hell is perſonated crying out:</p>
            <q>Diſcite justitiam moniti &amp; non temnere Divos.</q>
            <lg>
               <l>By me learne Iuſtice, and be wiſe,</l>
               <l>Nor doe the holy Gods deſpiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>From hence they feigne <hi>Nemeſis</hi> and <hi>Rhamnuſia</hi> hanging over the ſucceſſes of the wicked, and ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the courſes of their proſperity; from hence in their Tragedies if any horrible crime worthy a God to revenge it, was preſented, ſome God was then produced advancing his head from behind a frame or property: but theſe things were rare, and, as it were, forced by neceſſity, and but light compared to theſe which out of the Word of God wee learne concerning his providence, as of the haires of our head, which are all numbred; of the Sparrowes, not one of which falls on the ground without the will of God, of the wicked rejoycing in their follies while the hand of God
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19251:27"/> hollowes their pitte the deeper; of God ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our reynes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſeeing the ſecrets of our hearts; of giving an account before the Tribunall Seat of God, not onely of evill actions, but of an idle word.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> And as the people in the ſtreet, looking on the Dyall or the Clock, know by the hand what houre of the day it is; but are altogether ignorant of the hidden motions, and of the worke within that moves it ſelfe; but he that goes into the place where the Clocke is, doth with admiration behold the wheeles and poyſes of it, and proceeding from the wheele which moveth firſt, to that which is moved laſt, he obſerveth how the motions are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd and depend on one another: So the Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar ſeeth the events of things, as they expoſe themſelves to the eye and obſervation of all; but hee who is admitted into the Sanctuary of the Word of God doth wonder at the linked order of the divine Counſells, and poyſeth with himſelfe the weights of providence: So <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 73, confeſſeth that at the beginning he envyed the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of ungodly men, and was not a little afflicted to ſee them flow with bleſſings, not onely accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their deſires, but alſo above them, while the righteous and they who are called the people of God in full boles drinke deep of waters ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with gall, which affliction of his mind was eaſed after hee was entred into the Sanctuary of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> from whence, as from a Watch-Tower, he beheld the end of the Vngodly, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19251:27"/> that the happineſſe of men was not to be adjudged by the preſent condition of their ſtate; but by the counſell of God, and the laſt event of things: the holy man owed this his rectifyed judgement of humane affaires to the Word of God, from which in many places hee confeſſeth, that hee had derived the wiſedome of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/> Adde to this, that, if we had no other Maſter, but the Creatures onely, to inſtruct us in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, every man would frame a Religion to himſelfe according to his owne pleaſure, and as every Creature was moſt profitable to the life of man, accordingly divine honours ſhould be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to him; from hence it is that the Perſians worſhipped the Sunne, becauſe they ſaw nothing more faire, they found nothing of a more quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vertue then the Sunne; from hence it is that the Aegyptians worſhipped an Oxe, of which creature there is a ſpeciall uſe in manuring of the Earth; from hence it is, they worſhipped alſo the Bird <hi>Ibis,</hi> who with his horned beake did deſtroy the Snakes, and purged Aegypt from her Serpents; whereupon as every man became more renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, either by valour, or by the praiſe of civill pollicy, or by the invention and ſtudy of the Arts, hee was more eaſily exalted by poſterity into heaven, and numbred in the Catalogue of the Gods.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/> But did not the light of the Word of God ſhine downe from heaven, it cannot be related what pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19251:28"/> of Religion, what vaine obſervations men would fancie, with what painted fables would they delude themſelves and God, attributing thoſe things unto God, which would misbecome a man but indifferently ſober? This was the vanity that firſt brought Atheiſme into the World; for a man civilly wiſe, that beholds Cities and Nations to be diſtracted by contrary opinions, and all things to be full of fables, ſuffers himſelfe eaſily to be traduc'd to a beliefe, that Religion is but a meere invention, to which opinion <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſeemes to be more inclined, for in his booke expreſſely written on the ſame ſubject he endeavours to prove, that Atheiſme is more tolerable then Superſtition: and <hi>Cicero</hi> in his ſecond Booke <hi>De Natura Deorum</hi> doth affirme, that they are called ſuperſtitious who whole dayes doe offer prayers and Sacrifice, that their children may ſurvive them; and they are ſaid to be religious, who ſequeſter, and with care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full reverence touch thoſe things which apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the ſervice of the Gods; But, good man, he was altogether ignorant that this which he calls Religion is nothing elſe but Superſtition.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/> Neither is it to bee wondred at, that they were inclouded in ſo thicke a darkneſſe, on whom the light of Gods word not ſhone; for as the Nations which underſtand not the cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the ſtarres, or of the Sunne, confound the order of the Moneths and yeares; So the Nations to whom the Word of God was not revealed, did infinitely intangle themſelves in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19251:28"/> many errourts concerning Religion; for they who worſhip not God according to the rule preſcribed in his Word, are without God in the world, As the Apoſtle hath it in the Second of the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they worſhip millions of Gods, nay al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Samaritans came neere and next in conformity to the true Religion, acknowledging that they worſhipped one onely God, the Creator of the Vniverſe, the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and were ſigned with the ſigne of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, &amp; acknowledged <hi>Moſes</hi> too their Law-giver, yet becauſe they revolted from the rule of the Word of God, and by a ſtubborne ſeparation did divide themſelves from the Iſraelites, our Saviour ſaith in the Fourth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> that the Samaritans knew not what they worſhipped; So neceſſary it is, in the buſineſſe of ſalvation, to have God to leade us, and to make his Word our Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/> But when the light of Gods word hath once ſhined into a Nation, preſently all falſe Religions are blowen away, and the inventions of Mans braine vaniſh, and the kingdome of Sathan which preſerved it ſelfe in darkeneſſe, fals downe before the Light; then not unelegantly may be rehearſed that of <hi>David,</hi> in the 104. <hi>Pſalme: As ſoone as darkeneſſe is ſpread over the Earth, the Beaſts of the Forreſt come out of their Dens, and the young Lyons reare after their prey: but as ſoone as the Sunne ariſeth they hide themſelues in their Dennes and dare not come forth, but Man then goeth forth unto his worke and to his labour untill the Evening:</hi> Indeed when the darke
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19251:29"/> miſt of Ignorance overſpreads the Earth, Satan and his Miniſters triumph ſecurely like unruly Beaſts, but as ſoone as the Sunne of the word of God hath begunne to ſhine, they fly away that hate the truth; then doe the godly goe forth unto their labour untill the Evening; that is, they labour in the ſervice of God and the exerciſe of good workes, untill by a happy Death they arriue to the evening of their life.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="76"/> To come therefore to the true and ſaving knowledge of God, wee haue need of another maſter, and more bright inſtructions then thoſe which are learned out of the workes of the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or borrowed from humane reaſon: It was not enough for thoſe Wiſe men to haue ſought the Cradle of the Redeemer, to haue had the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of a Star, but they muſt further be inſtructed by the teſtimony of the Prophets: did we exactly underſtand the greatneſſe of the Stars, their moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, their vertues, and their diſtance, wee ſhould never come by theſe directions unto God, unleſſe the voyce of God ſhould withall informe us in the inſtructions of the Prophets and the Apoſtles, therefore the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> in the 19. <hi>Pſalme,</hi> after hee had ſaid, <hi>That the Heavens declare the glory of God,</hi> attributing ſo great an eloquence to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly bodies, although but ſpeechleſſe, that not a nation under heaven but heares them, he preſently paſſeth to the Law of God, leading us by the hand to a better maſter, to more cleare and certaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions; the Law of God (ſaith hee) is entire,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19251:29"/> converting the ſoule, the teſtimony of the Lord is true, giving wiſedome to the Simple.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="77"/> Neither doe theſe things appertaine, to excuſe thoſe who being taught by the onely workes of God, haue not attained to the knowledge of him; for although, without the inſtructions and the conduct of the Word of God they could not attaine to ſuch a knowledge of him, as is ſufficient to ſalvation, yet they are juſtly condemned be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they fought againſt the generall notions of Nature, and endeavoured to put out her light; neither vſed the inſtructions of the creatures to that advantage which they might; wherefore they are convinced by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt of the <hi>Romanes, For ſuppreſsing the Truth, and detayning it in vnrighteouſneſſe,</hi> and becauſe that when they knew God they did not glorifie him as God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> Neither ſinned they onely by their ignorance, but alſo by their perverſeneſſe and their pride; as the ſame Apoſtle in the ſecond of the <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> who ſaith, <hi>That hee who fals off from the ſervice of God to the worſhipping of Angels</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude into thoſe things which hee hath not ſeene, vainely putt up by his fleſhly mind; and in the 1. of the <hi>Rom.</hi> hee ſaith, <hi>When they profeſt themſelues wiſe, they became fooles, and were therefore delivered over to vile affections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> By this I thinke it is evidently ſhewed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, beſides the inſtructions which wee learne out of the workes of Creation and Providence, wee haue need of another doctrine, to wit the word of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19251:30"/> God; But wherefore God, who could without the preaching of the Word convert our hearts, and immediately infuſe into them the knowledge of himſelfe, had rather leade us to the knowledge of himſelfe, and by this knowledge to Salvation, by his Word, it is not curiouſly to bee ſought into: For God who reſerues the reaſon of his Counſailes to himſelfe, and is not ſubject unto any, is not to bee called to an account, neither is it for man to argue with God; nevertheleſſe the reaſon of this divine Counſell is evident, and it is eaſie enough to aſſigne the Cauſe; for be cauſe Death entered into the World by the eare, it pleaſed God that the doctrine of Salvation ſhould enter in by the ſame way too; And becauſe that Man fell by beleeving the words of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, it was fitting that man ſhould bee raiſed from his fall by beleeving the Word of God; for it was requiſite that contrary evils ſhould be cured by contrary Remedies; wherefore God ſends us by <hi>Eſay</hi> the Prophet to the Law and to the Prophets, pronouncing that it cannot be that without theſe, the morning Light ſhould ſhine on any; and in <hi>Luk. 16<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Abraham</hi> teacheth us, <hi>That it is in vaine to haue recourſe unto the dead, and to expect Revelations from thence, when we haue at hand the Law and the Prophets.</hi> Neither is it to be doubted, but that Chriſt, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſight unto the blind by annoynting his eyes with ſpittle, did ſecretly therby intimate, that, only that which proceedeth from his mouth illuminates the underſtanding, and ſcatters the darkeneſſe of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19251:30"/> naturall ignorance: Hence it is that in the hiſtory of the old &amp; new Teſtament, there are found examples of ſome holy men whom God chaſtiſed with blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as <hi>Ahia</hi> the Prophet, or with dumbnes, as <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> the father of <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> but of a religious man whom hee ſtrooke with deafeneſſe, and from whom hee tooke the ſenſe by which his Word ſhould bee conveyed unto him, there is not any Example in the Scriptures; but the Devill is called the deafe Spirit in the Goſpell, becauſe they who are poſſeſſed with him doe deafe their eares at the Word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> This Word of God was firſt delivered by the Oracle of his voice, afterwards God ſo pleaſing, it was commended to us in writing, and engraven in publicke Tables that it might neither bee raz'd by Oblivion, corrupted by Errour, or prophaned by reprobate Raſhneſſe; this is the Booke, which by excellence is called THE BIBLE, as if other bookes valued with this, did not deſerue to bee called Bookes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/> But among many and great Authorities which confirme the credit and prerogatiue of the holy Scripture, that teſtimony is moſt certaine, and aboue others of greateſt efficacie which the Holy Ghoſt doth giues it, unto it to wit, the ſecret pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Spirit with hidden ſtings, piercing the hearts of thoſe that heare and reade it, a power aboue all reaſon infinite; to expreſſe which in fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting accents all Eloquence is dull, all language barren, and words doe faint and faulter under the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19251:31"/> greatneſſe of the thing. Let <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> be read, or
<q>Princeps Romani Tullius Eloquij,</q>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tully</hi> the reputed Prince</l>
               <l>Of the Roman Eloquence.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Onely while they are read they doe affect, there being a kind of ſoft harmony and gentle titillation that ſtroakes the eare, but when the hearer is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, the ſenſe of that delight departeth alſo, as the face is ſeene no more in the glaſſe when the perſon is retired from it; But if there bee a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and attentiue hearer or reader of the Word of God, it will ſit deepe within him, and graven in his heart bee euer preſent, breathing forth Diuinities, governing the affections, cheering the heart, and finally renewing the whole Man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/> But becauſe this teſtimony is onely perceiued by thoſe whom God hath endowed with his Spirit, in whom the letter of the Word dead in it ſelfe is quickned, and as it were ſharpened by the Spirit of God, in vaine with this weapon doe wee fight againſt the prophane, who deride and reject what ever they haue not experienced, and meaſure the power and vertue of God by their owne ſottiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; how euer, beſides this efficacy of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there are many things more, which can ſtop the mouthes of Infidells, and giue both authority and beliefe to the holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/> And firſt of all, there is no other booke which in ſuch a ſimplicity of language hath ſo great a Majeſty, ſpeaking vnto Kings and Subjects with
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19251:31"/> equall Authority, for men howſoever they bee vnequall in dignity compared among themſelues, compared to God they bee all equall; As the Mountaines and the Vallies make both one plaine in the Globe of Earth, when Earth is compared vnto heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/> Satan the Ape of God imitating this Simplicity, whiles hee affects the roughneſſe of the Stile could not attaine the Majeſty if it; hee fancied the Etru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian diſcipline and the Salian verſes in a rude and rugged phraſe, but he forbade them to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd as being aſhamd of his owne doctrine, nay, he could not bee believed among his owne Prieſts to whom he did entruſt his Myſteries, whereupon <hi>Cato</hi> was wont to ſay that hee wondred how one Southſayer looking on another could refraine from laughter, becauſe acknowledging among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues the impoſtures of their profeſſion, by a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret combination they would nevertheleſſe coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfet themſelues as ſerious.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="85"/> Againe it is remarkeable that every booke bee it never ſo ancient, Compared to the antiquitie of the Bible will bee found but of a late edition, the Grecians fed on Acornes, yea their Names were ſcarce knowen in the World when Moſes wrote his five bookes intituled the Pentatenche, with which all the Philoſophy in the World cannot compare.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="89"/> 
               <hi>Homer</hi> and <hi>Heſiod</hi> the moſt ancient of the Greeke Poets liued at leaſt a hundred and fifty yeares after David, yet Davids inſpired Poems are diſtant as far
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19251:32"/> from <hi>Homers</hi> as heaven from Earth, or the fables of man from the truth of God, neither doth <hi>Plato</hi> diſſemble in the beginning of his <hi>Timaeus</hi> that the Aeygptians would ſay that the Grecians were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes boyes, who neuer could bee men of Age as being altogether ignorant of true Antiquitie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="86"/> Why ſhould I heere rehearſe the moſt ſtupendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous miracles and with what a Majeſtie the Law was pronounced, &amp; what were the wonders in Aegypt, and the Wildernes, and thoſe not actedin a corner, or before but a few witneſſes, but all Aegypt both beholding and repining at it, and before the eyes of ſixe hundred thouſand armed Men, and the moſt mightie Nation that was fed with Manna, which followed the pillar of fire conducting them, and heard the voice of the trumpet, who with horror did behold the burning mountaine, and flames of fire whirling high as heauen, invironed with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſmokes and thicke clouds of rowling darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneſſe; And that no man may conceiue that this was feigned by <hi>Moſes</hi> in fauour of the Iſraelites, with moſt terrible threatnings he thunders againſt that nation, and every where convinceth them of folly and pride, and Rebellion againſt God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="87"/> Now with what integritie <hi>Moſes</hi> wrote this, it is apparent, that hee conceales not his owne offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but rehearſeth the chaſtiſement wherewith God afflicted him, and that hee was commanded to die on the borders of the promiſed land becauſe hee beleeued not the voice of God; And how farre hee was from Ambition, wee may ſee by
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19251:32"/> this, that hee would not haue his ſonnes ſucceede him in his Governement, but elected <hi>Ioſhua</hi> that was of another tribe; And how ſmall the dignity of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſonnes was among the pireſts wee may learne out of <hi>Ioſephus, lib. 1. Orig. cap.</hi> 11. Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cites that in the diſtribution of ſacred things which was made by <hi>Dauid,</hi> the charge which <hi>Moſes</hi> poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie had, was but the keeping of the treaſurie, and the Gifts which were offered in the temple.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="88"/> Neither muſt wee leaue out, the Antiquitie and Certaintie of the prohecies, for by what inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could <hi>Eſay</hi> foretell the name of <hi>Cyrus</hi> and that hee ſhould bee a deliuerer of the Iewes 160 yeares before <hi>Cyrus</hi> was borne; Or what other but the Spirit of God could foretell to <hi>Ieroboam</hi> that a King ſhould bee borne of the Stocke of <hi>David, Ioſias</hi> by name, who ſhould overthrow and demoliſh their profaner Alters, and that, three hundred fiftie and ſixe moneths before it was done; What ſhall I ſay of <hi>Ieremie,</hi> who expreſſelie ſet downe the 70 yeares of Captivitie in Babilon; What of <hi>Daniell,</hi> who from the reſtauration of Ieruſalem to the death of Chriſt, preciſely numbers ſeventie weeks of yeares, that is 490 yeares, the predictions of the ſame <hi>Daniell</hi> of the foure Empires, and of the Kings <hi>Seluci,</hi> ſeeme rather to bee hiſtories then prophecies; Which may bee affirmed alſo of the prophecies of <hi>Eſai,</hi> of whom Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Paulinus</hi> ſaith, that hee ſeemes rather to bee an Evangeliſt then a Prophet; theſe things cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely could not bee ſuggeſted into the Prophets
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19251:33"/> by any other then by him onely, who as hee hath a foreſight of all things ſo hee hath an inſight alſo, and knows them well, becauſe that hee will doe them.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="89"/> The dignity therfore of holy Scripture is above all hazard or doubt of oppoſition, and the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of it is ſo great, that Chriſt himſelfe greater then the Law, and who inſpired the Prophets, was accuſtomed to defend himſelfe with the teſtimony of the Law and Prophets againſt the Phariſees, and therefore when many in defence of the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſacred Scripture have ſacrificed their lives, there is no man found, that in defence of <hi>Platoes</hi> or <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> opinion, yet ever ventured to encounter death; Indeed I could be content to ſay that <hi>Cleombrotus</hi> the Ambrocian was <hi>Platoes</hi> Martyr, who (as <hi>Cicero</hi> in his third <hi>Tuſculan</hi> doth relate) having read the Booke of <hi>Plato</hi> entituled <hi>Phaedo,</hi> where <hi>Socrates</hi> neere unto death diſputes of the immortality of the Soule, did force himſelfe into a headlong death; this man, I ſay, might bee called the Martyr of <hi>Plato,</hi> had he done this in any hope of ſalvation to be attained by <hi>Platoes</hi> meanes, and not through the tediouſneſſe of life.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/> Now the bookes of the myſteries of the Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and the Religion of the Druids are periſhed, the Hetrurian<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Diſcipline is extinguiſhed, and the Verſes of the <hi>Sybills</hi> are aboliſhed, only the holy Writ hath remained untouched, as having God its Authour; neither to extinguiſh it, could prevaile the horrible inſolence of <hi>Antiochus Epiphanes,</hi> or
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19251:33"/> the impious cunning of <hi>Iulian Caeſar,</hi> or the perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious writings of <hi>Lucian</hi> and <hi>Porphyrius,</hi> nay, theſe execrable perſons were the admirable examples of the Divine Iuſtice. It is knowne how <hi>Antiochus E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanes,</hi> conſtrained to raiſe his Siege, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <hi>Elemais</hi> through griefe of mind, in the flower of his age and Kingdome breath'd forth his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous ſoule: how <hi>Iulian</hi> in his very entrance into the Empire, ſtrooke through with an arrow, gave up his impure ſpirit: how (if we may beleeve <hi>Suidas</hi>) enraged dogs tore <hi>Lucian</hi> in pieces.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="91"/> Neither is that an Argument of little conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, to confirme the authority of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which <hi>Ioſephus</hi> writeth in the twelfth Booke of his Iewiſh Antiquities, <hi>Chap:</hi> 2. where <hi>Demetrius Phaleraeus,</hi> the Keeper of the Kings Library, ſpeakes thus to <hi>Ptolomaeus Philadelphus</hi> out of <hi>Hecataeus Abde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita,</hi> concerning the ſacred Bookes of the Iewes, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as being pure and holy, it was unlawfull that they ſhould be expreſt by a prophane mouth: the ſame <hi>Demetrius Phaleraeus</hi> relates out of <hi>Aristaeus</hi> that <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opompus</hi> having wrought into his ſtory ſome part taken from the ſacred Word, was for fourty dayes together ſtrucken with an Apoplexy, untill, by ſome reſpits of releaſement from his ſickeneſſe, he appeaſed God by his prayers, and deſiſted from his enterpriſe, being admoniſhed in a dreame that theſe things happened to him becauſe he intruded into holy things: In the ſame manner <hi>Theodoctes</hi> the Poet, having inſerted into a Tragedie of his
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19251:34"/> ſomething taken from the Word of God, being ſtrucke with blindneſſe, was inforced to abandon the enterpriſe which ſo raſhly he beganne.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="92"/> Agreeable to this is that which <hi>Clemens</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in his firſt Booke of <hi>Tapiſt:</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Booke of Womens habites, that Ieruſalem be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taken and razed by the Babylonians, all the Bookes of the Iewes were reſtored againe by <hi>Eſdras;</hi> their intention is not, that the holy Bookes were utterly extinguiſht and abolliſhed, and then againe reſtored by <hi>Eſdras;</hi> for ſo the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Bookes, which at this day we reade, ſhould not be the Bookes of <hi>Moſes,</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> or of <hi>Eſay,</hi> but of <hi>Eſdras,</hi> who by new inſpirations did compile them; the intention of <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> is, that the Bookes of the Old Teſtament, during the Captivity of Babylon, diſperſed, or but rarely and negligently tranſcribed, were digeſted by <hi>Eſdras</hi> into order, more accurately written, and reſtored to their native beauty.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="93"/> And ſince that time theſe bookes with ſo much Religion were obſerved by the Iewes, whom it pleaſed God to make the Library of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that if the booke had at any time fallen to the ground, they would enjoyne themſelues a ſolemne and extraordinary faſt; and at the end of every booke they did uſe to write, not onely the number of the verſes, but the number of the letters alſo; in which ſcrupulous ſedulity of theirs, the true honour due unto the Scripture doth not conſiſt, but hee doth reverence it as hee ought, who reads
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19251:34"/> it with ſuch eyes, as the conſtant wife doth the contract of her marriage, or the good Sonne doth his fathers Will, who never heares the Scripture mentioned but his heart doth leape, and his filiall affections earne, who by this rule doth compoſe, and ſquares all his life, his deeds and words, nay, and his thoughts alſo: But as young <hi>Samuel</hi> being awaked from ſleepe by the voice of God, lay preſently downe to ſleepe againe, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to be but the voyce of Man, and not of God; ſo the greateſt part of men, the word of God being heard, and they awakened by it, in a light feare they beginne a little to ſtirre &amp; ſtretch them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but by and by they fall againe into a ſleepe of vices, becauſe they heard this word as the word of man, and not as the word of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="94"/> What is contained in theſe bookes it would bee too tedious to deſcribe, it ſhall be ſufficient to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe unto the eye, the elements of Chriſtian Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, that wee may ſee in what things the true knowledge of God conſiſteth.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="95"/> The Scripture therefore teacheth, that Man was firſt created to the Image of God, endued with Holineſſe and Righteouſneſſe, and revolted from God by his owne conſent, and by the ſuggeſtion of the Devill, whereupon came ſin into the world, and by ſinne Death and Malediction; notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Image of God in Man is not ſo disfigured, that there remaine not certaine traces of it; to wit, a certaine perceiving of Divinity, and ſome graines of honeſty and civill juſtice,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19251:35"/> which notions that God might helpe, and that no man might excuſe his ſinne by pretending igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, God hath given his Law written by man, which Law is reduced to theſe two heads: <hi>To loue God with all our heart, and with all our ſtrength, and to loue our neighbour as our ſelues,</hi> which Law with great terrour hee pronounced in a voice, whoſe accents were thunders and ſhining with flames of Lightning, that the people might under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that their Lawgiver was armed, and who ſo deſpiſed his commandements ſhould not eſcape unpuniſhed; this dreadfull clauſe adjoyned to it, <hi>Curſed is he that continueth not in all things, which are contayned in the booke of the Law to doe them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="96"/> When therefore Man by nature prone unto ſinne cannot fulfill theſe Commandements; this Law were nothing elſe then the torment of the conſcience, and the miniſtery of Death, had not God according to his mercy releeved Man in this forlorne eſtate.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="97"/> Hee therefore in his appoynted time preſcribed by the Prophets, ſent his Sonne the everlaſting Word, the wiſedome of his Father, whom hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat from all eternity, who together with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the Holy Spirit is one God, into the world, and endued him with humane fleſh; ſo the Word was made fleſh, and God in vnity of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon aſſumed humane Nature without any diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Divinity, or mixture of the Natures; for it was requiſite that the Mediator betwixt God and Man, ſhould bee God and Man, and touch
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19251:35"/> both extreames by the Communion of Nature.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="98"/> In this Nature of Man, this Sonne of God, our Redeemer finiſhed the worke of our Redemption, perfectly fulfilling the Law, by expiating our ſins by his Death, and triumphing over Death by his Reſurrection, hee is the Author of eternall life to all thoſe that beleeue in him: Wherefore as the Sinne of <hi>Adam</hi> is imputed to all his poſterity, ſo the Righteouſneſſe of Chriſt is imputed unto all thoſe who by the Spirit of Adoption and faith in him are made the Sonnes of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="99"/> By this marke Chriſtian Religion is diſcerned, and diſtinguiſhed from all Religions which hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane reaſon hath invented, that it ſhewes the way by which onely we haue acceſſe to God by his Sonne who is the Way, the Truth, and the Life; that is, the true way to life: And though God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habites light which none can come unto, yet after ſome manner hee hath made himſelfe viſible in his Sonne, who is the Image of God inviſible, and God with us, whoſoever ſhall endeavour to come to God by any other way, hee ſhall find him a Iudge and not a Father, and the more he haſts, the more hee erres, and headlong fals into a certaine ruine.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="100"/> To the finiſhing of this worke of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the perſon of the Sonne was choſen rather, than the perſon of the Father or the Holy Ghoſt, for if the Father had beene made Man, and aſſumed our Feſh, there had beene in the Trinity two Sonnes, one by eternall Generation, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19251:36"/> by Generation in Time: Neither was there any thing more agreeable, than that hee who was the Middle in the perſons of the Trinity, ſhould alſo be the Middle betwixt God and Man, and bee the linke and tye of all affinity betwixt heaven and earth; And what could bee more apt and ſutable to the Wiſedome of God, than that we ſhould be reſtored into the Right and Degree of ſonnes, by him who is the onely Sonne of God, and that God ſhould renew Man by the ſame Word by which he created him, and that God ſhould ſpeake unto us by him, who is the Eternall Word of God, and by him ſhould teach us true wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome who is himſelfe the wiſedome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="101"/> This is that Doctrine which is called the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, which God hath left as a pledge in his Church, that by this prerogatiue it ſhould bee diſtingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from the reſt of mankind, which doctrine he hath commanded to bee publiſhed throughout all the world, by his Apoſtles and their Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, preſcribing, that thoſe who joyne themſelues to the Church ſhould bee baptized <hi>In the name of the Father and of the Sonne and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and that the people ſhould bee inſtructed in the faith of Chriſt by the preaching of the Goſpell, by which to the Penitent and Beleeving, Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes and everlaſting life is promiſed, and that the faithfull ſhould attend the ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt, in which hee ſhall raiſe up the dead, and taking into his knowledge an Account
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19251:36"/> of all Mans actions, ſhall render unto every one according to his workes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="102"/> By the Church I underſtand not onely the Church under the new Teſtament, which is called the Chriſtian Church, but alſo the whole Church in all Ages, whoſe beginning is deduced from <hi>Adam,</hi> and which ſhall laſt unto the End of the World; for the Scripture teſtifieth, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers before Chriſt were ſaved by faith in Chriſt; <hi>Abraham rejoyced to ſee my day and hee ſaw it, Iohn.</hi> 8. And <hi>Moſes</hi> preferred the reproach of Chriſt to the treaſures of <hi>Egypt, Heb. 11. And it pleaſed the Father to reconcile all things by the blood of the Croſſe, whether they were things in Heaven, or things in Earth, Col.</hi> 1. And there is no man of ſober underſtanding, that ever yet made doubt, but that theſe words of, <hi>Things in heaven,</hi> did comprehend the Patriarchs and the Prophets; to which purpoſe ſome of the Ancients haue not unaptly applyed an Allegory of a Branch laden with Grapes, which hanging on a ſtaffe was carried on two mens ſhoulders, by him that went formoſt they underſtood the Church of the old Teſtament, by him that came after, the Church of the new Teſtament, and by the branch of Grapes, Chriſt himſelfe; for the old Church ſaw not the comming of Chriſt, becauſe it went before in order of Time, but this latter hath Chriſt ever before her eyes and beholds him come: Nevertheleſſe the Branch of Grapes is as much the food of one as of the other, for Chriſt equally unto both
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19251:37"/> Churches conveigheth life and foode ſpirituall.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="103"/> Theſe are thoſe inſtructions in which the true and ſaving knowledge of God conſiſteth; a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge which farre tranſcends all other Arts and Sciences; The Sciences are all either contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or practicke, the excellence of the Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platiue conſiſts in theſe three things, the Dignity of the Subject, the Certainty of the Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the Perſpicuity of the Inſtructions; the excellence of the Practicke conſiſts in theſe, the Excellence of the End, the Aptneſſe of the Meanes, and the Rules to attaine that End.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="104"/> In Divinity that part is contemplatiue, which treateth of the nature of God, and of the workes of Creation, Gubernation, and Redemption; but that part which treateth of the offices of Piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, and Charity towards our Neighbour is practicall; for although in this there bee great need of Contemplation, yet all this Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is directed to the Practicke, in one as in the other, Divinity doth infinitely excell all Sciences:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="105"/> The Subject of the Part contemplatiue is God himſelfe, betwixt whom and the body of Man, or twixt Lands and Chattles, the <hi>Subiects</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Phiſicke</hi> there is no compariſon, but in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty it wonderfully tranſcends them all: For whatſoever the Philoſophers doe diſpute concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the chiefe or principall good, are ſo different among themſelues, ſo contrary one unto another, that their chiefe good ſeemes rather to bee groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on opinion then on nature. <hi>Augustine</hi> in the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19251:37"/> nineteenth booke <hi>of the Citty of God,</hi> reckons up out of <hi>Marcus Varro,</hi> a hundred and foureſcore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing opinions of Philoſophers concerning their <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> or Chiefeſt Good; and Phyſicians doe rather ſuſpect, then ſee the inward affections of the bodies, and the cauſes of diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; and hereupon it often comes to paſſe, that in pretence of curing the diſeaſed, officiouſly they kill them: But how great the uncertainty of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Law is, the infinite diverſity of cuſtomes and countries, the endleſſe diſcord of municipal Rights, and of the Roman and Barbarian Lawes, doth plainely teſtifie: but the foundations of Divinity ſtand ſure and unſhaken, being laid by the hand of God himſelfe, and are more firme then Heaven or Earth: <hi>The Heaven and Earth ſhall paſſe away, but my words ſhall not paſſe,</hi> ſaith God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="106"/> Neither doth it any thing derogate from this certainety, that Men in the buſines of Religion are divided into ſo many Sects, and diſpute with ſuch contentious heate concerning the interpretation of the Scripture; for this doth not ariſe from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainety of Gods Word, but from the pravity of Man, who wilfully doth blind his owne eyes, and takes delight to ſtumble in ſo faire a way, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting Religion to his belly, and by depravation of the moſt certaine things, with full Sailes doth fly to Avarice or Ambition; For whoſoever will not deſtine himſelfe to a peculiar and ſet opinion, ſhall find in the Holy Scripture many cleare and evident ſentences, wanting no Interpreter which
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19251:38"/> abundantly wil ſuffice him both for faith &amp; maners.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="107"/> I confeſſe in the Scriptures there are many things full of obſcurity but if the pious ſtudent ſhall weigh them well, hee ſhall find them either prophecies or figures, and not foundations of faith or of the nature of thoſe things which are neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to Salvation; for God by plaine and eaſie things doth inſtruct us to Salvation, and by obſcure ones doth exerciſe us in prayer, or workes in us ſobriety, or pulling the wings of our curioſitie doth retaine us in the bounds of modeſty: And this muſt bee a received Maxim, that the leaſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge derived from the word of God, is more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then the exacteſt knowledge of earthly things; For a little of the knowledge of God faithfully received doth abundantly ſuffice to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame our minds with the loue of God, and to leade our liues both well and happily.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="108"/> The End Remaines by which Divinity, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever there is of Arts or Sciences by a tranſcendent Diſtance doth excell; For the Politicks onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>informe a man as he is a Citizen, the Oeconomicks as hee is the maſter of a family, But Divinitie doth inſtruct him as hee is a man, and diſcourſeth not of the parts of Life but of the Whole, neither doth it propoſe unto it ſelfe any particular or ſubordinat end, but the laſt end of all, <hi>viz.</hi> eternall bleſſedneſſe, which conſiſteth in an vnion with God, to which end it is requiſite that other Ends and our whole eourſe of Life ſhould be obedient, vnles peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we would bee carefull of our life in ſome little
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19251:38"/> portions and pieces of it, but in the whole be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrifts, &amp; ſo of many litles (as we thinke wiſely laid together) one entire folly ſhould bee made, and there would bee a good Lawyer, a good Phyſitian, a good Senator, but a bad man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="109"/> But the meanes which Divinitie doth vſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to this laſt End, which is our vnion with God, namely Faith in Chriſt and the ſtudie of good Workes are ſo apt, ſo certaine, ſo well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, that no doubt is to bee made of them, vnleſſe wee would make a doubt of the promiſes of God who is Truth himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="110"/> Finally the knowledge of God (God himſelfe recording it) is ſo much to be eſteemed, that though to glory in other things is an extreame vanitie and the firſt point of folly, in this onely God would haue us with a religious pride to glory, in our ſelues; For thus ſaith he in the ninth of <hi>Ieremy, Let not the Wiſe man glory in his Wiſedome, neither let the mighty man glory in his might, let not a rich Man glory in his riches, but let him that glorifieth, glory in this, that hee vnderſtandeth and knoweth mee, that I am the Lord who excerciſe Iudgement and Righteouſneſſe on the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="111"/> Now ſeeing there may bee gathered from the knowledge of God many and excellent fruits through the whole courſe of our life, this is aboue all the moſt principall, that we cannot maſter our Corruptions, or ſtop our deſires in their Careere with a ſtronger reyne than with the knowledge of God; For hee that knows God, knows him to bee
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19251:39"/> a ſearcher of the ſecrets of the heart, whoſe eyes cannot bee curtain'd with the flattering clouds of lying or hypocriſie, to whom Accounts are to bee given of every idle Word; wherefore the holy Scripture did aſſigne this the Cauſe, of the Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſonnes of <hi>Heli,</hi> they were wicked men, the ſonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> not knowing the Lord, and <hi>Hoſea</hi> the 4. <hi>Becauſe there is no knowledge of God in the Land, perjury, and Lying, and Stealing, and commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Adulterie hath broken forth, and bloud toucheth bloud;</hi> On the contrary from the knowledge of God ariſe all examples of Vertues; wich <hi>Eſay</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth, <hi>Chap. 11. They ſhall not hurt nor deſtroy in all my holy mountaine, for the Earth ſhall bee full of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Lord;</hi> And truly a holy Man who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders alwaies, that God beholds him, will ſo liue in private as in publicke, ſo in publicke as in the Temple, ſo in the Temple, as before the eyes of God who is his Iudge, his Maſter and his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; Neither doth Satan open a wider window vnto all kind of vice than by perſwading Men that God looks not downe on things ſo low; For then a deepe ſleepe overwhelmes the Conſcience, and the feare of the Iudge being taken off, the barres are broken and Men dare doe any thing, running headlong into all kind of Villanie, although re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain'd a little by the power of the law or by the feare of Infamy.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="112"/> Neither is the knowledge of God of little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in chaſing from vs all reſtleſſe Cares, in calming the troubles of our mind, and in ſilencing
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19251:39"/> the tongues of Murmurers; For hee that knowes God, knowes all his workes to bee as full of Iuſtice as of providence, to complaine of whoſe provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence as it is vnrighteous, ſo to oppoſe it, is not onely vnprofitable, but Raſh and Dangerous; And hee who is aſſured that God ſo workes that even evills themſelues doe turne to Good to thoſe that feare him, doth ſecure himſelfe in his care and Loue.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="113"/> The ſame knowledge of God is greatly profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in teaching vs to obſerue an honeſt and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vſe of earthly things, leſt by an vngratefull oblivion wee bury his bleſſings, or abuſe them vnto Riot or to luſt, or reſemble the beaſts that drinke of the River never thinking of the fountaine from whence thoſe waters flow; For hee who knowes God, knowes him to bee the Author of all Good things, and in that title doth pay homage to him, and is induſtriouſly wary leſt thoſe things which God hath given vnto vſe and matter of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, be corrupted by ingratitude or abuſe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="114"/> What ſhall I ſay more, ſeeing, without the knowledge of God it is impoſſible for vs to know our ſelues, for then the bubbles of our Pride ſinke downe, and our plumes doe fall, when wee looke on God; For as long, as a Man lookes on himſelfe or compares himſelfe with inferiour things, hee takes himſelfe to bee a creature of ſome reckoning, and applaudes the humour, overcome with a vaine and flattering opinion of his ſtrength or Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he preſents himſelfe before the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunall
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:19251:40"/> ſeate of God, hee is preſently touch'd with an apprehenſion of his weakeneſſe, and his naturall pollutions and deformities preſent themſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and is invironed with ſo great a Light, that he is inforced to confeſſe that the Light of his Vnderſtanding is but vtter darkeneſſe; In the ſame manner, they that onely behold the things which are before their feete, beleeue their ſight is good and cleere enough, but the ſame Men when they behold the Sunne, haue ſtrait their eyes ſo blinded that they are compelled to confeſſe, that the ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt diſcretion of their eye is both darke and dull, when it turnes it ſelfe vnto heavenly things.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="115"/> Seeing then ſo great is the exellence of this divine knowledge, and the fruit thereof ſo abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant that it may bee extended into every part and portion of our life: I cannot but here lament the condition of humane vnderſtanding which in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling things doth expreſſe a moſt ſubtle and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Induſtry, but in the knowledge of God alone, doth languiſh in a drowſie ſloth; For how Rare is hee that diſregardeth not theſe ſacred ſtudies to addict himſelfe toi things that tend to the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage either of publcke or private dignity? How many beate their braines in curing the bodies and skinnes of others, who within their owne, haue Dropſie humours? How many ſit in the ſeate of Iudgement to decide the Differences of others, which are themſelues at diſcord with God, and conſider not that he muſt iudge them? How many are expert in the Account of Numbers and Lines,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19251:40"/> whoſe owne lives are Irregular as being altogether without the knowledge of God? So ſtrange be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides is the garbe and Condition of humane things, that we preferre delights even aboue neceſſities; So the Confectmaker is valued aboue the husband man, and wee thinke the embroiderer to bee a more Subſtantiall fellow then the Taylor; And commonly thoſe ſtudies are more eſteemed that make for gaine, then thoſe that inſtill into our minds the elements of divine Wiſedome; It falls out with theſe, what <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> reports, to haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne the ſuiters of <hi>Penelope,</hi> who becauſe they could not obtaine the Miſtreſſe, enjoy'd their deſires with her Maides; For the Arts are the handmaids of divine Wiſedome, neither doe they deſerue a place in the Ranke of honeſt diciplines if they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe not themſelues to bee attendants on it, theſe are thoſe handmaids which the Divine Wiſedome ſendeth forth, as it is recorded in the ninth of the Proverbs.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="116"/> Peradventure ſome peremptory puny will heere ſtep forth and to depreſſe Divinitie beneath other Sciences, will alleadge that it is ſubordinate unto them, and that it borrows of them many things, as Ornament from Rhetorick, Acuteneſſe from Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, the knowledge of the chiefe principles from the Metaphyſicks, the nature and helpes of vertues from the Ethicks, and that the Student in Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, after hee hath received the headed ſpeares from Divinitie, doth hurle them with greater force and certainety with the armes of Philoſophy; Finally,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:19251:41"/> that Divinitie ſhould bee vnarmed and unnerved, ſhould it be deſtitute of the helpe of the Arts.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="107"/> But they who breath forth theſe empty noiſes, doe not diſtinguiſh Divinitie from the Divine, that is the Science from the Man; As when the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician profeſſeth the Art of Phiſicke onely for gaine, this is not the end of the Art but of the Man; The Divine indeede every where doth ſearch and collect together, the aides and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Eloquence, but Divinitie doth not therevpon increaſe either in excellence or Abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, for it ſubſiſteth of it ſelfe and needeth not the aide of any; Neither haue thoſe <hi>Coryphaei</hi> in Divinitie, the Prophets and Apoſtles begg'd theſe ornaments; their Simplicity being more powerfull than all Eloquence, and their Majeſtie of greater vertue than all acuteneſſe of Logick or Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy; As the chaſt Matron is moſt adorned, that hath on no ornaments at all, leaving to the vnchaſt or the vnbeautiful, their falſe and artificiall dreſſes, and borrowed Complexions; What if the Iudge doth ſell his purple, or the mercenary Lawyer the braver hee is cloath'd, doth eſteeme his tongue at the deerer rate, muſt the Taylor therefore advance his needle aboue the law? One Science is ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate vnto another, when it borroweth it's principles from it, or, when the Concluſions in the ſuperiour Science, are made the principles of the inferiour, ſo the Opticks are ſubordinate to Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metry, and Muſicke to Arithmetick; Or when the End of one Art is ſubordinate to the End of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19251:41"/> another, So the Art of making bridles, is ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din'd to the Art of Horſe-manſhippe, and that Art is ſubordinate to Military Diſcipline; But no ſuch thing is to bee found in Divinity.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="118"/> But if the Divine doth gather ſome of the more graue and morall ſentences out of the writings of the Philoſophers, hee doth not that for want or for neceſſitie, but to ſet a bluſh on Chriſtians cheekes, who by their prophane life diſhonour their moſt holy profeſſion, that ſo they who will not heare God, may heare Men, endued only with the light of Reaſon, and by their teſtimonies and accuſations may bee as well convinced as aſhamed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="119"/> But neither doe wee graunt that the Divine takes theſe things from the Philoſopher either by intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or by loane, ſeeing he doth rather force them from him as from an vnlawfull owner, for whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſparks there are of Religion in the whole world, they ought to bee brought to the Altar of God, and whatſoever inſtructions there are that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne true vertue, they appertaine to his Temple, no otherwiſe then the veſſels of Gold and Silver, taken from the Aegyptians in pretence of Loane were converted after to the building of the Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="120"/> Hither therefore being bound let vs labour with wind and oares, and to arrive to this knowledge let vs plough the Deepes of this preſent World, with ſweating induſtry; For if the Philologer when from the Rubbiſh of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie, hee finds out words hoary with Age and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19251:42"/> covered with duſt, or when he expoundeth ſupee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annuated Cuſtomes about meates or habits, bee heard with great attention and applauſe, what eares and Attention ſhould wee lend to them, who vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold things more Ancient than heaven it ſelfe, and declare the Wiſedome of the Ancient of Dayes, drawen not from the defectiue Ciſterne of the Critick, but from the vnfaddom'd deepes of the Oracles of God? If the Lawyer bee heard plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of eaue-droppings, of tenements, or of Wills, how, with more purged eares ſhould the Divine, not diſcourſing of drops of waters, but of the fountaine of Life it ſelfe, not of the tenure of houſes, but of the liberty of the Spirit, not of the teſtament of dying men, but of the Will of the living God?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="121"/> Labour after this then, you that haue all a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to bee good, and that you may attaine to the true knowledge of God, endeavour that no ill affection may corrupt, or wanton ſaftneſſe may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate your reſolutions; for if the Heathens deferred long, and kept at the doore thoſe that were to be inſtructed in the ſervice of holy things, if they were not admitted into <hi>Ceres</hi> Temple, but after many ſighs and tedious preparations by often purifyings; what manner of man ought he to be, whom God admits into the Chancell of his moſt ſacred diſcipline? And if <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in the firſt of his <hi>Ethicks,</hi> and the 3. Chap<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would haue his hearer of civill ſciences, to be neither <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, young in age or manners, how
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19251:42"/> much more requiſite is it, that all youthfull heates ſhould be cooled in him, who is to addreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to that Science, to which all other ſciences are but ſervants?</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="122"/> Nevertheleſſe wee muſt take heed, leſt while too much wee employ our ſelues in this ſtudy we offend God by our ſedulity; which comes to paſſe, when not content with what belongs unto ſalvation, wee labour in things unneceſſary, and by a prophane curioſitie ſearch after thoſe things which exceed the compaſſe of our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or ſobriety: For as heretofore when the Law was publiſhed, there were bounds ſet round about the Mountaine, which it was death to breake thorow, ſo there are certaine bounds ſet round the doctrine of the Goſpell, which it is ſacriledge to tranſgreſſe: A religious ignorance is better then a curious knowledge; and as the fire giueth light to thoſe that are a farre off, warmeth thoſe that are neerer and in a reaſonable diſtance, but conſumeth thoſe that approach ſo neere to touch it; So God illuſtrates all with ſome light, yea even the moſt removed from ſalvation, but thoſe that are admitted neerer, he warmes them with his loue, and inſpires them with his Spirit, but who with a wilfull curioſitie intrude themſelues, and even dare invade him, he overcomes and deſtroyes them with amazements, <hi>Who ſeeketh after Majeſtie ſhall bee conſumed with the glory of it.</hi> This corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion beganne in <hi>Adam,</hi> affecting that knowledge of Good and Evill which onely appertaineth unto
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19251:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:19251:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:19251:44"/> God; wherefore as in the eating of the Paſchall Lambe, the Iſraelites were to feed onely on the fleſh and not to meddle with the bones; ſo in the doctrine which inſtructs us in the knowledge of God, wee muſt labour after thoſe things which ſerue for the nouriſhment of our ſoule, and abſtaine from thoſe which by their hardneſſe would breake our teeth, and turne the edge of our underſtanding: then onely in the knowledge of God ſhall we obſerue a meane betwixt an affected negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and a ſawcie curioſitie, when we ſhall referre all our knowledge and meditation to piety and manners, and to the loue of God.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Le Sr de la Primaudaye en ſes Quatrains.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <lg>
                     <l>L'aeuvre excellent des cieux, &amp; l'entour, &amp; le ſpace,</l>
                     <l>Rendent leur Architecte admirable à tous yeux:</l>
                     <l>Mais ſa divine loy reſtaurant l'ame en mieux,</l>
                     <l>L'eſleue ſur ce tout pour voire Dieu face à face.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The glorious Vault, and fabricke of the skies,</l>
                     <l>Preſents their wondrous Maker to all eyes:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Law divine, reſtoring ſoules by grace</l>
                     <l>Mounts them o're all, to ſee HIM face to face.</l>
                  </lg>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="extracts">
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:44"/>
            <head>THE CHOICEST SENTENCES TAKEN out of this preſent treatiſe of the knowledge of GOD.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>In the collection onely whereof I have followed the Copy of <hi>Mounſieur Derelincourt</hi> Miniſter of the Hague, which if they be thought either too tedious or impertinent, it ſhall be ſome protection to me, that I had ſo reverend an Example.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>RVTH is ſo affected to the Mind as Light unto the Eye.</hi> Sect. 3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The true knowledge of God is the moſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute perfection of the mind.</hi> Sect. 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That in all Men is inherent an apprehenſion of a God, it is manifeſt by experience and the teſtimony of all Ages, amongſt whom there is none ſo wild or barbarous that hath not received ſome forme of Religion, and that eſtabliſhed under moſt grievous penalties, for this is no written but a natiue Law, to which we are not taught, but made, not inſtructed by precepts but by the principles of Nature.</hi> Sect. 7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From nothing to ſomething is an infinite diſproportion.</hi> Sect. 24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the beames of Light diſperſed over all the World, doe flow from one beginning, namely the Sunne, and as num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers proceed all from Vnity, and in the Body of Man, as all the Arteries and Vitall Faculties proceed from one heart, ſo every Being doth depend and is ſuſtayned by one chief and Soveraigne Being.</hi> Sect. 24.
<pb facs="tcp:19251:45"/> 
               <hi>God is not onely the efficient Cauſe of all things but the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall alſo, as the Apoſtle witneſſeth to the Hebrewes, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> That God is for whom and by whom all things are. Sect. 25.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The End is alwayes the formoſt in the Intention, and the Efficient Cauſe is moved by it.</hi> ibid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſt true is that of</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>in his ſecond booke</hi> de Gen. cap. 10. <hi>that the perpetuall durance and continuance of things ought to bee imputed to the Simple and daily Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sunne from the Eaſt into the Weſt; but that Generation and Corruption doth ariſe from the oblique courſe of the Sunne and planets through the Zodiack, whiles according to their ſituation they change their Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects, and by their acceſſe neerer to us, or receſſe farther from us, the Affections, and the Qualities of the things doe differ.</hi> Sect. 28</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the Eſſence of God cannot be expreſt by words, ſo it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be conceived by the Vnderſtanding, for a thing infinite cannot be comprehended by a thing finite, and the inacceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible light of God doth dazle the underſtanding.</hi> Sect. 39.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From the diminution of the knowledge of God would ariſe a diminution of his loue, and by the ſame contempt where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the knowledge of the divine Nature is neglected, the knowledge alſo of the divine Will would bee deſpiſed.</hi> Sect. 42.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The life of a Wiſe man is nothing elſe but a Returne to God, and the way to God is by the ſtudy of Piety and Iuſtice.</hi> Sect. 43.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Maker of time is before time, and above it, neither is his duration meaſured by it; for as the infiniteneſſe of God doth not onely conſiſt in this, that hee is not circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by limites, but moſt eſpecially in this, that hee is all in every place; ſo his eternity likewiſe conſiſts not in this onely that he is without beginning and without end, but rather in this, that his life is not a motionary courſe,
<pb facs="tcp:19251:45"/> but a perpetuall reſt, and in which there is no ſucceſſion of parts.</hi> Sect. 56.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As to a man ſitting on the banke of a Riuer, only that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is preſent which is obſerved by him in that inſtant moment, and poynt of time, but that part of the River is not preſented to his eyes which is not yet come to him, or but now gone from him; yet the ſame man, were he exalted into the upper region of the aire, might behold the whole River, and at one aſpect obſerve both the fountaine and the coruſes of it; ſo by the eye of God, who is obove time, together, and in one moment is obſerved the whole flux of tranſitory things, neither in him is there addition or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, becauſe all things are preſent with him.</hi> Se. 56.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thoſe perfections which are diverſe and ſcattered in the creatures, in God are one and the ſame perfection.</hi> Se. 57.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God making the body of man of earth, did conforme his mind to humility, and a religious lowlineſſe, by remembring him of his deſcent and ignoble parentage.</hi> Se. 67.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The happineſſe of men is not to be eſteemed by the preſent condition of things, but by the Counſaeile of God, and laſt event of all things.</hi> Sect. 71.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is neceſſary in the buſineſſe of ſalvation to have God our leader, and to make his word our rule.</hi> Sect. 74.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Becauſe that man did fall by believing the words of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, it was fitting that man ſhould be rayſed from his fall by believing the Words of God: for it was requiſite that contrary Evills ſhould bee cured by contrary Remedies.</hi> Sect. 79.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scripture teacheth that Man being firſt creaeted to the image of God, indued with holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, revolted from God by his owne conſent, and the ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of the Devill, whereupon ſinne came into the world, and by ſinne death and malediction, notwithſtanding the i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage of God is not ſo deformed in man, that there remains not certaine traces of it, to wit, a certaine apprehenſion of
<pb facs="tcp:19251:46"/> Divinity, and ſome graines of Honeſty and civill Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</hi> Sect. 95.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Though God inhabits light which cannot be attained to, yet in ſome manner he hath made himſelfe viſible in his Son, who is the image of the inviſible God, and God with us, whoſoever ſhall endeavour to come to God by any other way, he ſhall find him a Iudge and not a Father, and the more he haſts, the more he erres, and headlong falls into a certaine ruine.</hi> Sect. 99.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Phyſicians doe rather ſuſpect then ſee the inward affections of the Bodies, and the cauſes of Diſeaſes, and hereupon it often comes to paſſe, that in pretence of curing the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, officiouſly they kill ihem.</hi> Sect. 105.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As there are may be gathered many and excellent fruits from the knowledge of God; ſo this is above all the moſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall, that we cannot bridle in our vices, or ſtop our deſires in their careere with a ſtronger rein, then with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God; for he that knowes God, knowes him to bee a ſearcher into the ſecrets of the heart, whoſe eyes cannot be curtaind with the flattering clouds of lying or hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, to whom accounts are to be given of every idle word.</hi> Sect. 111.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To complaine of Gods providence, as it is unrighteous, ſo to oppoſe againſt is raſh and dangerous.</hi> Sect. 112.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Without the knowledge of God it is impoſſible for us to know our ſelves; for then the bubbles of our pride ſinke downe, and our plumes doe fall when we looke on God.</hi> Sect. 114.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then only in the knowledge of God ſhall we obſerve a meane betwixt an affected negligence and a ſawcy curioſity, when we ſhall referre all our knowledge and meditation to piety, and manners, and to the love of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:46"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:19251:47"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
